<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The policy of the clergy of France, to destroy the Protestants of that kingdom wherein is set down the ways and means that have been made use of for these twenty years last past, to root out the Protestant religion : in a dialogue between two papists : humbly offered to the consideration of all sincere Protestants, but principally of His Most Sacred Majesty and the Parliament at Oxford.</title>
            <title>Politique du clergé de France. English</title>
            <author>Jurieu, Pierre, 1637-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 236 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 108 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46369</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J1210</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18016</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12728539</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12728539</idno>
            <idno type="VID">66400</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46369)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66400)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 359:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The policy of the clergy of France, to destroy the Protestants of that kingdom wherein is set down the ways and means that have been made use of for these twenty years last past, to root out the Protestant religion : in a dialogue between two papists : humbly offered to the consideration of all sincere Protestants, but principally of His Most Sacred Majesty and the Parliament at Oxford.</title>
                  <title>Politique du clergé de France. English</title>
                  <author>Jurieu, Pierre, 1637-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 211, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Bentley and M. Magnes ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: La politique du clergé de France.</note>
                  <note>Written by Pierre Jurieu. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Protestants --  France.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  France.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66400:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:66400:1"/>
            <p>THE POLICY OF THE CLERGY of <hi>FRANCE,</hi> TO Deſtroy the Proteſtants OF THAT KINGDOM. Wherein is ſet down the Ways and Means that have been made uſe of for theſe twenty Years laſt paſt, to root out the Proteſtant Religion.</p>
            <p>In a Dialogue between two Papiſts.</p>
            <p>Humbly offered to the Conſideration of all ſincere Proteſtants; but prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally of his Moſt Sacred Majeſty and the Parliament at <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Bentley,</hi> and <hi>M. Magnes,</hi> in <hi>Ruſſel</hi>-ſtreet <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> near the <hi>Piazza.</hi> MDCLXXXI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:66400:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:66400:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE POLICY OF THE <hi>CLERGY</hi> of <hi>FRANCE.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="conference">
               <head>The Firſt Conference.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>The Pariſian.</speaker>
                  <p>THIS, Sir, is a happy Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter for me; who thought you were at <hi>Paris:</hi> Methinks you very much neglect your ancient Friends. I ought not to have been the laſt to whom you ought to have made known your arrival, ſince there is no body more diſpoſed to do you Service than my
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:66400:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſelf. What brings you hither? Does it lye in my Power to ſerve you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>The Provincial.</speaker>
                  <p>I am infinitely obliged to you, Sir, for all your Civilities and Offers. But I have not at preſent any Affair of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance; the deſign of diverting my ſelf, of ſeeing my Friends, of learning what paſſes in the World, and of loſing ſome of the ruſt of the Province, has brought me to <hi>Paris.</hi> And I am over-joyed that my good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune has made me meet with the man I honour the moſt, and whom I have ever had in my memory; but out of whoſe thoughts I feared I had been a long time baniſhed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>I knew you as ſoon as I ſaw you, and have ey'd you this quarter of an hour, to be ſure my ſight had not deceived me. I likewiſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved you was in earneſt Diſcourſe in that Book-ſellers Shop, with a Gentleman I had never ſeen before. Who is he? He ſeems to be well bred, and appears like a Perſon of Quality.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:66400:3"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>It is an old <hi>Hugonot</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and a great Friend of mine. We have made ſeveral Campaignes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and having found much Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and Sincerity in him, I never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented the great engagements I have had with him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>Have you much Commerce with People of that Religion?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>Some: The moſt part of my Neighbours are of it; and there are few of them that I know, but who are honeſt People.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>For my part I have no deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with them: Not but that I inform my ſelf very particularly of their Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, and hear them often ſpoken of; but I have no acquaintance amongſt them. And beſides, by what I have heard ſay, I believe that ſuch a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce is dangerous.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I am not of your Opinion: I pretend to be as good a Catholick as another; but I never found in thoſe People any thing that ought to oblige me to avoid them. They are of a very grateful and eaſie Communication; they do not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:66400:4"/>act the part of Converters in the World: We hardly ever diſcourſe of Religion together; and when it is mentioned, it is always after a very modeſt manner. We talk pretty of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of their Affairs, but without heat and paſſion. As to the reſt I have always found them good <hi>French-men,</hi> brave, ſincere, faithful in their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, true Friends; and you know this is all that is demanded for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation and Civil Life. For the reſt, I do not penetrate into their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, to know if they do their Duty towards God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>I am very glad to hear you talk thus; for I am not unwilling to have a good Opinion of all the World. But if you have Friends in that Party, counſel them to retire betimes; it falls, and thoſe who do not quickly abandon it, run the riſque of being oppreſſed under its Ruines. It is a Religion very much decryed, which every where runs into decay, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in this Kingdom. Some memory that had been preſerved of the Services they had done the Crown,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:66400:4"/>had hitherto upheld them: At pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent this is abſolutely worn out. The Diſguſts they meet with at every ſtep, diſcourages the moſt zealous. They quit a Party that is an invincible Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacle to their Fortune: And as things go, morally ſpeaking, they are not to laſt ten Years longer: They will be brought back without doubt into the Boſome of the Church, from whence the boldneſs of their preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Reformers has drawn them. This is a thing that is made no longer a myſtery of. You ſee how <hi>P. Maim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg</hi> ſpeaks of it in his Epiſtle to the King, at the head of the Hiſtory of <hi>Lutheraniſm.</hi> I hope, ſays he, to write ſuddenly the Riſe and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of <hi>Calviniſm</hi> at the ſame time; and is mightily tickled with theſe hopes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I am over-joyed you are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len upon the Point. It makes a great noiſe in the Provinces, and I have ſpoke of it often to perſons who have not intirely ſatisfied me. You are here at the Source of Affairs, and I muſt beg you would be ſo kind as to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:66400:5"/>inſtruct me therein. But we muſt chuſe a more Convenient place than the Pavement of St. <hi>James</hi>'s Street, which is not much better than the Sea Shore, where <hi>P. B</hi>—makes <hi>Ariſtus</hi> and <hi>Eugenius</hi> to have ſo long Conferences, notwithſtanding the heat of the Sun. You know the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor has been rallied for it; and though we were not acquainted with this Story, the ſeaſon and hour would oblige us to ſeek a ſhade and ſhelter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>Let us go to my Houſe, which is but three ſteps from hence; and be ſo kind as to take part there of a mean Dinner, after which we will ſpend the Afternoon as you ſhall think fit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I accept the offer without more ado; by which procedure, I fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, you will perceive me to be ſtill the ſame man, without Ceremony, you know I formerly was.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>They enter the</hi> Pariſian's <hi>Houſe, they Dine there, and after Dinner they go into a Parlour, where the Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation is thus renewed.</hi>
               </stage>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:66400:5"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>Since you have aſſured me you have no buſineſs to day, and that we ſhall ſee no body: I demand of you this Afternoon, for the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting me with the manner that is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for the reducing the <hi>Hugonot</hi>-Party to the Catholick Religion. This Affair holds all <hi>France</hi> in ſuſpence. The Catholicks are in great impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to ſee the Succeſs of the hopes that are given them therein. The <hi>Hugonots</hi> on their part ſay not all they think; I ſee them very much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm'd. They chear up themſelves: We hope, ſay they, that God will not abandon the Party of truth. They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call into their memories what they ſtile their Deliverances. But with all this, I do not believe them very ſafe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>They have certainly no great reaſon to think themſelves ſo, for great Deſigns are on foot againſt them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>But the King, is he of the Party?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>Do not doubt it. The King is a good Catholick, and wiſhes the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:66400:6"/>Reduction of the <hi>Hugonots</hi> to the Church, with as much zeal as any of his Subjects. But beſides that, he is more than any man poſſeſſed with that noble paſſion which is called the love and deſire of Glory. It is repreſented to him, That after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made all <hi>Europe</hi> tremble, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd ſo fair Provinces, taken ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Cities, made ſo many Sieges, and won ſo many Battels, nothing can be more worthy of him, and more capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of rendering the memory of his Reign Glorious, than the re-uniting the Religions in <hi>France.</hi> He has hearkned to it, and will forget no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for the accompliſhment of this Deſign. The King does not naturally love to vex his people, and if he was left to act according to his inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, things would not be carried on ſo violently; but he is puſhed on, and is not left at quiet.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>It is not however believed that violent means ſhall be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed; that is to ſay, Sword, Fire and Baniſhment.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>If ſome Bigots were liſtened
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:66400:6"/>to, nothing ſhould be ſpared. But the general vein of the Kingdom does not go ſo: The King does not love violence: Beſides, how weak ſoever a Party may be, when it is puſht to extremity, it is capable of giving a deſperate blow: It was not obſerved that this Conduct ſucceeded in the laſt age. And in fine, the King, whoſe principle aim is to make himſelf formidable to his Neighbours, does not deſign to depopulate his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries: And doubtleſs they would be conſiderably depopulated. if the <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonots</hi> were deſtroyed by the Sword, or chaſed away by Baniſhment.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>It is well known, that the Kings Proſpects are very oppoſite to thoſe; for he has made ſeveral Ordonnances to hinder his Subjects from leaving the Kingdom. It is likely that the <hi>Hugonots</hi> have a very great ſhare in them; they are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to go ſeek re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſe elſewhere: They muſt ſtay and be expoſed to the ills that are deſigned them; and that they may at length change, being wearied with ſo many Fatigues, or invited by ſuch hopes.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:66400:7"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>It is ſo, it is not to be diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled. See here then the manner by which it is pretended to compaſs the great Deſign of re-uniting them to the Church. It has been obſerved by experience, that there are two things that give root to Hereſie in a State. The firſt is, the great Liberty that the Hereticks have of preaching their Doctrines. The Second is, the Conveniency of Life, when they are ſuffered to live in a profound Peace, and enjoy Charges, Employes, and all the other Dignities and Priviledges which the other Subjects enjoy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>It is certain, when a man is born of a Religion, and that he finds therein all the Repoſe, Riches, Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and Honour that he could wiſh, he has no great mind to change it, how little zealous ſoever he may be.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>That's true, and therefore during fifty Years there was not ſo many Converſions ſeen, as within theſe five Years. The Edicts given in favour of the <hi>Hugonots</hi> by <hi>Henry</hi> the 4th. and confirmed by his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour <hi>Lewis</hi> the 13th. granted
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:66400:7"/>them great Liberties. In the Cities, where they were moſt numerous, they poſſeſſed one part of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratures; they had Chambers of the Edict in the Parliaments, and likewiſe divided Chambers in the Provinces, where they were moſt numerous. They avoqued all their Cauſes to theſe Chambers, that the zealous Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick might not do them injuſtice. They exerciſed all manner of honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and gainful Profeſſions, with the ſame liberty as the Catholicks. They were Counſellors and Attorneys at Law, Phyſicians gathered in a Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Faculty. They were recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into Arts, they carried on Trade; they likewiſe entred into the Kings affairs as well as others. In War no diſtinction was made between them and the Catholicks: Nothing was conſidered, but Merrit and Fidelity, and Service, and Courage. They were received into all the Military Dignities, and had Penſions. They were Collonels, Brigadeers, Major-Generals, Lieutenant-Generals, and even Marſhals of <hi>France,</hi> comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:66400:8"/>Armies in Chief. On the other part, as for what concerned the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of their Religion, they very free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enjoyed what had been granted them: They had places appointed from the time of the Edict, for their Sermons: Every Gentleman, having High Juſtices, was as a little Soveraign in his Houſe: He might aſſemble by the ſound of the Bell, all the Religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries thereabouts; he made a Pariſh in his Houſe, and no body diſturbed him. The Biſhops were uſed to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer thoſe people in their Dioceſſes: They had even engagements with the Principals of this Party. The <hi>Hugo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not</hi> Lord made no ſcruple of viſiting my Lord the Prelate; and the Prelate, on the other part, lookt with a good Eye upon the <hi>Hugonot</hi> Gentleman. Thus they lived in a very great Peace. But it was viſibly perceived that the Hereſie took deep root by the favour of that repoſe, as ill Herbs are increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the gentleneſs of the Spring.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>The State the Kingdom had been in for a long time, had without doubt contributed to the tranquility
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:66400:8"/>the <hi>Hugonots</hi> enjoyed. A War of thirty Years with <hi>Spain,</hi> a long Mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, Civil Broiles, and Forreign Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, had hindered the thoughts of them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>That is certain: For, after all, our Kings, who bear with juſtice the name of moſt Chriſtian and Eldeſt Sons of the Church, have never loſt the deſign of deſtroying Hereticks. But their Prudence has obliged them to ſuſpend the uſe of the means they deſigned to make uſe of for that end.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>As for <hi>Henry</hi> the 4th. I do not think this can be ſaid of him. He had treated with them with ſincerity. He was of opinion he had received great ſervices from them; he had been a long time of their Religion: He only quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it, that he might quite diſſipate the League which covered it ſelf with the Cloak of Catholicity. And we very well know, that this remnant of Inclination that he had preſerved for them, coſt him his Life. After his Death, during the minority of <hi>Lewis</hi> the 13th. and the Miniſtry of the Marqueſs <hi>d' Ancre,</hi> the Affairs of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:66400:9"/>Court and State were in ſuch diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that there were few thoughts of extirpating the <hi>Hugonots.</hi> It is true, that Cardinal <hi>Richlieu</hi> took from them their Cities of Surety; but it was ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of a Politick prudence, than any zeal of Religion. He ſaw that it was a State in a State, and that thoſe Cities were retreats for Rebels and the Diſcontented; but in the bottom he ſought not their ruin. His en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements were too ſmall with the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and was too able a Politician to ruin a Party, of whoſe Fidelity he might always be aſſured. It may likewiſe be ſaid, with more aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, that Cardinal <hi>Mazarin</hi> never thought of extirpating Hereſie. The Good man, though an <hi>Italian,</hi> and a Neighbour of the Church, had no great zeal for it, Riches were his only Divinity. It is very well expreſſed in one of his Epitaphs, <hi>Si Coelum ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitur, habet.</hi> He never ſought any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way to go to Heaven th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n that of Rapine. Eſpecially he never thought of this way to Heaven, which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Converſion of Hereticks. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:66400:9"/>his Miniſtry was attended with ſo many Traverſes, and he was ſo hard put to it to defend himſelf againſt ſo many Enemies, that it cannot be imagined he had ever any other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects than ſuch as tended to the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of his Family, and the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of his Fortune. Thus I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it may be ſaid, that the Deſign of ruining the Party of the pretended Reformed in <hi>France,</hi> has been laid ſince the Year 1660.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>I grant that the Project was not well formed till after the Peace of the <hi>Pyrenees;</hi> and ſee after what manner it was reſolved they ſhould proceed in it. Thoſe people, ſaid they then, muſt be deprived of the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty they have of preaching their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. By theſe means they will be no longer inſtructed, and will become ignorant of their own Tenets. Their Temples muſt be raiſed, and the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their Exerciſe taken from them. Their Miniſters muſt be perſecuted, ſome of them baniſhed, others im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, others deprived of their Goods by great Fines. Every thing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:66400:10"/>they do muſt be imputed as a Crime. Nothing is more eaſie than the ſurprizing them. They cannot preach their Religion without preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt the Catholick Religion; and there is not an Expreſſion, but what might produce a Proceſs. By this means the people will be terrified, Fathers and Mother diſguſted, and will not eaſily put their Children to the ſtudying Divinity for the making them Miniſters. Beſides this, they muſt likewiſe be diſturbed in all kinds, and be deprived of their Charges; and expelled from all Employes both of Peace and of War, and removed from Court, and baniſhed from the Kings Houſe, and likewiſe from the Armies both by Sea and by Land. Their Children muſt be taken from them, and be inſtructed in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Religion. They muſt be daunted by threatnings, and tempted by hopes, terrified by ſufferings, and invited by benefits; when they have once changed Religion, they ſhall be forbidden upon great puniſhments to return to the Religion they have quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:66400:10"/>Their liberties muſt be dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by little and little, and when it is reduced to a ſmall thing, and that their number is very much leſſened, on a ſudden all their Edicts ſhall be revoked.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>This ſeems to be very well concerted. The firſt thing that this Deſign produced, was the Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that the King made ſhortly after the Peace of the <hi>Pyrenees,</hi> by which he ordered Commiſſioners to take Cogniſance of the Infractions of the Edict of <hi>Nantes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>That is true: The <hi>Hugonots</hi> fell then into the Snare that was laid for them. They imagined that this Declaration was advantagious to them, and fancied, that by the means of theſe Commiſſioners, they ſhould have ſatisfaction for all the Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venſions that had been made for the Edicts and Declarations which were favourable to them; and ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traventions from that time were in no ſmall number.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I can aſſure you, that there were but few who were thus trap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panned.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:66400:11"/>They were before very well acquainted, that a great deal of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief was deſigned them, and the moſt penetrating judged that there was ſomething more couched under it than they could think of.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>It was a thing the beſt imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that poſſibly could be: For by Virtue of this Declaration, they were obliged to repreſent before theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, all the Titles by which they enjoyed their Temples, and the liberty of exerciſe of Religion in each place. And by theſe means, more than the half of their Temples were Condemned, and above the third part of them were raiſed: And after the manner they proceed in this Caſe, it is impoſſible any ſhould ſubſiſt; at leaſt there will ſo few remain, as not to make a number.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>How ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>Firſt, You know that a long Peace makes People negligent; no ſureties are taken, when no danger is ſeen. The <hi>Hugonots</hi> lived under the Faith of the Edicts and the Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations for above ſixty Years. They
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:66400:11"/>imagined they had no need of Titles, becauſe they had been ſo long in poſſeſſion: Inſomuch that they took but little care to preſerve the Titles of their eſtabliſhment. After the Edict of <hi>Nantes,</hi> Commiſſioners were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated by the King, for the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this Edict. They went to the Places where there was any difficulty. They gave Acts of eſtabliſhment for ſome places to Preach in, but not for all. For where there was no difficulty nor Proceſs to be tryed, they gave no judgment. In the places where the Commiſſioners had given Acts of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhment, becauſe they were not neceſſary, having found the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wholly made, they laid hold of the advantage, and condemned them becauſe they could not ſhew a Title they never had, and which was thought they had no occaſion for. In the places where the Commiſſioners had given acts of eſtabliſhment, if thoſe acts were not ſhewn; though they gave very evident marks of them, and that they had other pieces to which thoſe referred, no regard
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:66400:12"/>was had of them. In ſuch places where the firſt Titles were found, they found nullities in them; and you know it is not difficult to bring this to paſs where there are none. The moſt part of their Temples are founded upon a certain Right that they call Poſſeſſion, founded upon one of the Articles of the Edict of <hi>Nantes,</hi> which ſays. That in all the Places where the exerciſe of the <hi>R. P. R.</hi> ſhall have been in the Years 1596, and 1597, it ſhall be made there, and continued. Proofs were demanded of them, that Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons were Preached in ſuch a place in the Years mentioned by the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſtop you there. Had they need of Proofs and Titles, for a benefit they had been in Poſſeſſion of above ſixty Years? Was not there Preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for them? It is ſo general a Right, that it may be called the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. There is even Preſcription for Crimes. Thirty Years makes Preſcription every where, and the <hi>Hugonots</hi> had been in poſſeſſion above twice thirty Years.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:66400:12"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>They laughed at all this. Such Temples were raiſed as were more ancient than the Edict. To return to what I ſaid they were demanded proofs of their Poſſeſſion, and it was impoſſible for them to produce them. Firſt, the proof by Inqueſt is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, becauſe there are no people living of that time. The proofs by writing are, either Regiſters of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, or of Baptiſme, or Conſiſtorial Papers, or Acts of their Synods. As for Regiſters of Baptiſmes and of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, they will not receive them; they ſay that they Marry and Baptize every where, and that this cannot be a proof that they have had in a certain place, a Temple and a Publick Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe. As for Acts of Conſiſtories, and of Synods, it is difficult for them to produce any; becauſe that that time was Calamitous in the higheſt degree, by reaſon of the War of the League. They had not the liberty of aſſembling, nor of making acts of the Reſolutions they took: However they did not fail to produce a conſiderable number of them. But all this did nothing, no
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:66400:13"/>regard was had to them; nay, there is even no regard to the Reſolutions of the Counſel and the Parliament made for the eſtabliſhment of their Temples. And to tell you it in a word, the Catholick Commiſſioner has ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret orders, not to find any Title good, and to condemn all. It is true, that there is one of the <hi>R. P. R.</hi> joyned in Commiſſion with him, without whom nothing ought to be judged. But it is only for form ſake; this Catholick Commiſſioner does all. He alone inſtructs the Proceſſes, and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times judges them alone. If <hi>Hugonos</hi> complains of a Contravention to the Edicts, he is not heard. If a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick will complain of a pretended Contravention, he obtains all that he demands againſt them. In the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their Temples, the <hi>Hugonot</hi> Commiſſioner is either corrupted, or frightned; they deceive him, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe him to confirm one Temple, if he will conſent to the demoliſhing of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. And in fine, if nothing can be obtained of him, the Catholick Commiſſioner condemns, the Deciſion
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:66400:13"/>is made, and this Deciſion is ſent to the Counſel, where they ordinarily pronounce upon the judgment of the Catholick Commiſſioner, without further examination. Only for the keeping ſome appearance of juſtice, ſometimes of thirty Deciſions they will let the <hi>Hugonots</hi> gain one, that they may ſay to them, you ſee that Juſtice is done, when it is found that you have reaſon on your ſide.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I likewiſe oftentimes hear the Country Gentlemen complain of the troubles they are put to for the Sermons they cauſed to be preached in their Houſes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>Neither have they been ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon that Article. <hi>Henry</hi> the 4th. believing he had received great Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices from the Nobility of this Party, granted to all the Lords of High Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice the power of cauſing Sermons to be preach'd in the places of their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode, to receive there all people, and even to aſſemble them by the ringing a Bell: This occaſioned them a great number of Sermons. Not that at Court great ſtreſs is laid upon theſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:66400:14"/>eſtabliſhments, becauſe they pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh with the Gentleman's Family, who maintains them, or ceaſe when he turns Catholick. Now Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ruin themſelves by the expence they are at; and oftentimes to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver themſelves by ſome Employ, which gives them the means of Subſiſting, they change Religion, and are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted. Thus the Family decaying, or becoming Catholick, the <hi>Hugonots</hi> are chaſed away. However it has been indeavoured by ſeveral Decrees, to ruin theſe ſorts of eſtabliſhments. It has firſt been declared, that High Juſtices newly erected, were not granted to have this Priviledge, when they fell into the Hands of <hi>Hugonot</hi> Lords. They have enlarged this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the time of the Edict, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring they will not allow that publick exerciſe to be made in all the Lands e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected in High Juſtice ſince the Edict. But interpret the Article of the Edict of the Lands which were at that time in Right of High Juſtice: They e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven proceeded much farther, for it is pretended that the Lords have no
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:66400:14"/>Right of cauſing Sermons to be preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their Houſes, at leaſt if they do not ſhew that the Lands which they poſſeſs in High Juſtice, were at the time of the Edict in the hands of Lords of the <hi>R. P. R.</hi> and in poſſeſſion of cauſing Sermons to be held there. It is true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> is laſt Article has not been yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> every where with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> rigour; but it is an Affair that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> eaſily returned to. In the mean time theſe <hi>Hugonot</hi> Lords are forbidden to have any ſign of publick exerciſe in that part of the Houſe where preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is performed. They have cauſed the Bell and Seats to be taken away: And this is done, for fear that in time it might take the form of a place of poſſeſſion. They are likewiſe forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to have preaching out of their Houſe, and the Precincts of their Court. And for the more ſafety, a decree was made by which it was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to the Miniſters Preaching in the High Juſtices and in the Houſes of <hi>Piefarons</hi> to come to their Synods, and to enter themſelves in the Tables of theſe Synods. It is true, that they
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:66400:15"/>have obtained reſpite to the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this arreſt; as alſo to the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of another Order, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded their Miniſters to reſide in the Places where they preached, which had obliged the Miniſters who preach at <hi>Charinton</hi> to ſtay there, and quit <hi>Paris.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe reſpites that the King has granted, make appear that this Prince is good natur'd, and that he would give them much more repoſe, if he was not continually ſolicited by the Clergy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>I do not at all doubt it: But happily we have near his Majeſty ſuch perſons as never leave him at reſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that point. It is the whole buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Counſel of Conſcience. The Clergy has Informers, who only employ their thoughts for the inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting new Edicts as the <hi>Financiers</hi> have, who think of nothing but the means of augmenting the Kings Revenues.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>Will you make an end of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming me what is done to deſtroy their Temples?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhould be too long if I would ſay all. For within theſe twenty
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:66400:15"/>years ſo many orders have been iſſued to that end, that a great Volume is compoſed of them, and there is not one but what tends to their ruin: I aſſure you that nothing is neglected and that our people are watching on all ſides to deſtroy them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I hear them often complain of the deceitfulneſs of their Antago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>th is, they cry up the Maxim againſt them; <hi>Dolus, an vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus quis in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> requirat?</hi> I ſee that by thoſe who ſollicit me, and who put affairs into my hands againſt them. Falſe pieces are produced which of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes paſs for good. I'll give you an Example which will make you laugh. The Clergy of <hi>Niort,</hi> a City of <hi>Poitou,</hi> ſolicited the deſtruction of a Temple that the <hi>Hugonots</hi> have there. Their Deput<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> preſented an Order of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d the Year, 1601, or 1602. which ordered that the Temple of that City ſhould be raiſed; becauſe it had been only ſuffered in the City by Toleration, for the ſafety of the <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonots;</hi> who could not do their Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:66400:16"/>in the Field, becauſe of the Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guers. This Order having been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to the Advocate of the Party, he diſcovered that there was upon the Banks of the <hi>Loire</hi> between <hi>Orleans</hi> and <hi>Blois,</hi> a great incloſed Burrough, or little City, called <hi>Mer,</hi> in which were many <hi>Hugonots.</hi> This Order had been made againſt them. The Clergy of <hi>Niort</hi> had met with this piece by chance: They had in the word <hi>Mer,</hi> parted the laſt ſtroak of the <hi>m,</hi> and made it an <hi>i,</hi> they had made the <hi>e</hi> an <hi>o,</hi> inſomuch that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theſe changes it was read <hi>Nior.</hi> But the misfortune was, that in this Order there was mention made of the <hi>Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guers</hi> of <hi>Orleans,</hi> who made incurſions, and came to pillage. There was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe mention made of a certain Lord of <hi>Mer,</hi> and ſeveral other things of that Nature, which had no more refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to <hi>Niort</hi> than to <hi>Rome.</hi> Thust he piece was convicted of forgery.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>This is a ſtrange Cheat; the Curate who had falſified this piece, and had produced it, was not he pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed?</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:66400:16"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>And what puniſhment ſhould have been inflicted on him? All the ill he came to by it, was, that he loſt his Proceſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>Since we have ſeen the Principal things that are employed to ruin the Temples of the <hi>P.</hi> Reformed, be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to inform me of the other means that are, or will be made uſe of, to oblige them to quit their Religion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>You know that Fears and Hopes are the two great Machins that ſet minds a going. It was believed, that in doing them a great deal of hurt while they remained <hi>Hugonots,</hi> and a great deal of good after their Converſion, would draw in a great Number.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>This is an infallible means. How many people are there, who are of a Religion by chance, rather than by choice; who are not at all fixed in the Religion of their Fathers? who continue of it becauſe they were born ſo, and that they find therein their Conveniency? Having neither Piety nor Devotion, they little care of what Religion they are. How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:66400:17"/>Catholicks do you believe we have, who are not of Gods Religion but of the Kings, and who would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continently change if they were in a State where they could not have Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployes but upon that Condition?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>I know there are but too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. Wherefore theſe people are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of their Charges, and all hopes of coming to them. Their Nobility has conſumed themſelves as well as ours by their great Expences. Being become poor, they continue however vain and ambitious. You know that the moſt part of the Grandees have no other Divinity than their Grandeur, and that they would Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice all things for the maintaining it. Theſe people have appeared at Court, the King has graciouſly received them, they have been careſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, they have had part in all the pleaſures, and have had none in the Employs; that is to ſay, they have been permitted to ruin themſelves ſtill more in the great Scene of the Court, and by great expences: By this means they have took a reliſh to the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:66400:17"/>World. It is there that the zeal of Religion uſually diminiſhes: For there is no ſurer Remedy to Cure Bigottry than to come to Court. In the mean time they were perpetually told, you are of a Religion that is no longer of the mode; as long as you continue of it, nothing will be done for you; turn Catholick, and you are ſure to have Penſions, and Governments, and Regiments, and Brevets of Duke and Peer, and Staffs of Marſhalls of <hi>France.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I eaſily conceive that young ambitious minds, libertins and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, cannot reſiſt ſuch temptations, and thus they have been deprived of all their perſons of Note.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>They have been a long time put to trouble about Civil Charges and Magiſtrature. When they had purchaſed any ſuch Employ, they were ſtopt at the Seale, they were conſumed in Sollicitations, and were oftentimes after this ſent back, if they were not recommended by ſome Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Lord, who made their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs his own. But in ſine, this was tireſome, and of a ſudden they were
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:66400:18"/>rendred incapable of all Charges of Magiſtrature: Their divided Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulats were taken from them in <hi>Langue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dock,</hi> inſomuch that a ſmall Mayor of a Village is not ſuffered of that Religion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis true, I ſaw the other day a man from <hi>Cevennes,</hi> who told me hat in their Mountains they are all <hi>Hugonots,</hi> and that there be great Burrough Towns, where there is not a Catholick beſides the Curate. Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that it is not known how the Kings Edict ſhall be executed in thoſe places, for they will be obliged to cauſe Perſons to come 24 leagues from thence to exerciſe the Conſulats.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>There were a great many people who had part in the Kings Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs and Finances, which raiſed Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies amongſt them. They had had Intendants of the <hi>Finances,</hi> who maintained by their Commiſſions a multitude of mean people. The King has newly taken from them this means of ſubſiſtance, and they have been forbidden to have any part in the Affairs of the <hi>Finances,</hi> either dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly or indirectly. Which is the moſt
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:66400:18"/>terrible blow for them that can be imagined. For in ſine, it may be ſaid that it was the only way that was left them, to raiſe themſelves, to make a Fortune, and to acquire Riches.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>This puts me in mind of what I heard an old Miniſter ſay the other day, in a <hi>Hugonot</hi> Houſe where I was. The King, ſaid he, does us more good than he believes, in depriving us of Charges, and removing us from the <hi>Finances.</hi> The firſt entertained to our Vanity, and ruined our Families: and the Second brought us baſe Riches, which cauſed great miſchief our Party. So ſoon as a Citizen by his Traffick and Management, or by the means of his Parents had gained four or five hundred pounds a Year, he would needs be diſtinguiſhed. To that end he bought a Charge, and to maintain the Dignity of it, he ſpent beyond his Revenue. The beſt Managers laid nothing up: Their Riches, which in a heap was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing conſiderable, was no longer ſo, being ſhared amongſt ſeveral Children. Thus the Son of the very firſt Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:66400:19"/>ruined a Family his Father had raiſed. Whereas had they lived privately, they would have aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented their Stocks, and left their Children at their eaſe. As for em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploys in the <hi>Finances,</hi> the ill they have done us, is not to be expreſſed. They are certain means of enriching our ſelves by ſtealing from the King, or ſucking the blood of the people; both of them odious Crimes, and which draw the Curſe of God. Theſe people acquired money with great eaſe, wherefore it coſt them nothing. They fell into all manner of expences Luxury, and Vanities. The rich Branches of their Family, who were raiſed higher by Birth, and by Rank, would not ſuffer themſelves to be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed by theſe upſtart Families. Wherefore they exceeded in their expences, and ruined themſelves out of emulation. When we are poorer, perhaps we ſhall be more ſober and modeſt, ſince we cannot be ſo by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation. It is a great honour that is done us, not to ſuffer us to be Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans and Levyers of Taxes. This was what that Miniſter ſaid.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:66400:19"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>This is fine for a Sermon, but few people would be of this Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters Opinion. In the bottom they will ſee how many perſons this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prives them of. There are already great ones of the <hi>Hugonot</hi> Party, who are turning Catholicks, they will be followed by ſeveral others, and theſe great Heads will draw a Multitude of ordinary people, who labour and live under them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>My Miniſter foreſaw this; and added that it would immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happen, but that it would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>The truth is, that its a blow once given, whoſe effects will not laſt long for Converſions: Neither is it what is looked upon as moſt conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. It is a great point, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken from them the Chambers of the Edict, and the divided Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. Theſe bodies having been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly eſtabliſhed for them and in their favour, rendred them conſiderable, without reckoning that they had Preſidents, and the half of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors in the divided Chambers: This
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:66400:20"/>made appear they were ſtill held in conſideration. At preſent they are abandoned to injuſtice and violence. When they have a Catholick <hi>Anta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goniſt</hi> they are ſure to loſe their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs; and when both Parties are <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonots,</hi> that which gives hopes of changing Religion is certain to gain his Cauſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I was in <hi>Languedock</hi> when the divided Chamber of <hi>Caſtelnauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> was ſurpreſſed, and that the <hi>Hugo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not</hi> Counſellors were ordered to go to <hi>Tholouſe</hi> to be parted in the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. Theſe poor people were in a conſternation that cannot be deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed. They ſaid the King ſent them to Slaughter. They related to me ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Tragical Events which had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap>d either by the fury of the people <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> injuſtice of the Parliament of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> againſt them. Amongſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>things they told me that two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Counſellors, going one day <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> their Chamber, were hanged up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Court without any form <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:66400:20"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>The truth is that City is much changed ſince the time of the <hi>Albigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> it is paſſed into another extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: For it muſt be confeſſed that the zeal for the Catholick Religion is there accompanied with too much violence. To return to the Subject of our Converſation, What has been done to become Maſters of the <hi>Hugo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nots</hi> Children is extreamly well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certed. Firſt it has been ordered that Maids at the age of Twelve Years, and Boys at Fourteen, ſhall have the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of making choice of their Religion. You know that it is at that age that the Yoke appears heavy to Children; becauſe it is the age in which they muſt make choice of a Profeſſion, they are obliged to work, and it is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of them to begin to leave off the liberties of Child-hood. They have not yet any love for Religion, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes they have but very little knowledge of it. The Yoke of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and that of puniſhments being hard to them, they ſeek only the means to ſhake them off. To help them in the Execution of this Deſign,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:66400:21"/>there is eſtabliſhed in the Cities where the <hi>Hugonots</hi> are moſt numerous, Houſes of the Miſſion, and Propagati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Faith, into which the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious Children retreat under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of turning Catholicks. When they are in theſe Houſes, their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents are not permitted to ſee them, and they are lightly inſtructed; ſome days after they make abjuration of Hereſie, and they are made to ſign the act: After this they have ſome li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty given them, becauſe they are hindred by the Declaration againſt Relapſes, from returning into their former Religion. They are often times returned to their Fathers and Mothers, who are obliged to anſwer for them. And if the Children eſcape, and go away out of a Libertine hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, their Fathers and Mothers are accuſed of having ſent them out of the Kingdom; and upon this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text a Proceſs is formed againſt them, and they are ruined.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I have likewiſe heard ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Schools, now you are talking of Children.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:66400:21"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>There is an Order iſſued out, by which it is forbidden them to have more than one Maſter of a School, in every place where they have exerciſe. It is to oblige them to ſend their Children to Catholick Schools, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there are places where it is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely impoſſible that ſix School. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters can teach all the Children. And thoſe who ſhall go to Catholick Schools, endeavours are uſed to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them privately, and make them turn.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>For my part I avow to you, that I find that Article which regards Children very ſevere: I can hardly comprehend how liberty can be given to a Maid to make choice of a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion at an age we would not give her leave to chuſe a Petticoat. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, I hear them very often complain that they proceed farther than the Kings Declaration permits. They ſay that their Children are took from them before the age appointed by the Edicts; and when they demand the reaſon of it, they are laughed at. The Intendants who are Judges of theſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:66400:22"/>and other Infractions, put them off for whole Years, till that the Children may have attained the age of 12 or 14 years, and then they cauſe them to make their Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. When the Mother is a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, the Widdow of a pretended Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, according to the laſt Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations the Children ought to be inſtructed in the Religion of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But the Mother makes ſure of them, cauſes them to be inſtructed in her Religion, and no ſatisfaction can be had for it. They likewiſe ſay that their Children are often taken up in the Streets, are ſhut up in Cloiſters, and they never hear more of them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>All theſe complaints are not without ground. But what injury does this do them? Their Children are ſaved, and endeavours are uſed to ſave them themſelves.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I am told that a Decree has been lately made, which concerns the holding of their Synods.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>It is that henceforwards Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Commiſſioners ſhall be given them on the Kings part. It is a ſtep
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:66400:22"/>towards the depriving them of all li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of holding their Synods. By which means will be known their ſtrength and weakneſs; it will be known what Miniſters are capable of being gained. Diviſions will be ſown amongſt them, ſome will be won by promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, others daunted by Fear: In fine, their very Intrails will be known; and it will be a great means for the deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them. Beſides the Decrees that are made for the ruining them, others are obtained for the rendring of them infamous. They are forbidden to ſet up Flower de Luces, either within, or without their Temples, as if they were unworthy of bearing thoſe marks of honour; and as if they were not good <hi>French</hi>-men. All their principal Seats are ordered to be taken down in their Temples, and all the [Balliſters and Rails raiſed. The Biſhops have obtained a Decree, by which it is ordered, that during their viſit in the places where there is exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of that Religion, it ſhall be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted out of reſpect to the Catholick Religion, as if thoſe people were
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:66400:23"/>
                     <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Mahometans.</hi> This ſeems but a ſmall thing; but however it helps forward, and ſtrikes deep into the minds of the people, augments the averſion they have againſt the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> and diſpoſes them to quit a Religion, for which they ſee there is ſo much Averſion and Contempt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>The Decree that has been lately made to forbid their Midwives, and all others of their Religion to lay Women, is a thing that terribly vexes them. It is not to be deſcribed the terrour this has caſt in moſt places into the minds of moſt part of their Women with Child. For there are a great many Cities, where there is not one Catholick Midwife, who has any skill in that Art; and there are ſome where there are none at all. I have it from good hands, that in places, where this Order has been open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly publiſhed, the terrour of it has caſt ſeveral Women in Labour before their Times, and occaſioned their Death.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>This Arreſt is an eſſential point; wherefore all the former dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties muſt be paſſed over to put it
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:66400:23"/>in execution. When their Women are recovered from their firſt frights, it will be as convenient for them to be laid by Catholicks, as by Women of their own Religion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>But what will they do in thoſe places where there are no Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Midwives?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>Send for them from other places. Did you never know that Jewiſh Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wives have been ſent from <hi>Avignon</hi> to ſeveral Cities in <hi>Languedock?</hi> It is till that Catholick ones can be ſent thither. They will not at firſt be ſo very expert, and will coſt ſome Women their Lives; but for a greater good, ſome ill is to be permitted. For in fine, by theſe means they will be uſed by little and little to loſe the Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience they are to be deprived of. It is one of their Articles of Faith, that the Baptiſme of Faith is not good. They muſt at preſent ſuffer this Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of Faith to be forced from them. But there is another myſtery couched thereunder which is not yet time to reveal, and which will be manifeſted in its time. Shall I tell you my Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion?
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:66400:24"/>We have not yet touched the moſt important Declarations that have been rendered againſt them; it is the Declaration againſt Relapſes, and the Decree which was lately made, forbidding any Catholick, upon pain of Baniſhment, loſs of Honour, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcation of goods, to turn and be of the pretended Reformed Religion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I have ſeen theſe Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and make the ſame judgment as you do of them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>It may be ſaid that thus two thirds of the affair is done. The Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Conſcience that had been grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, conſiſted only in theſe three points. The firſt of being permitted to live in the pretended reformed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when born of it. The ſecond, having leave to change and be of it; though not born of it. The third, the being free to turn to it again; though they had once abandoned it. The laſt is extinguiſhed by the Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration againſt Relapſes. The Second, by this laſt Declaration, which forbids a Catholick to turn <hi>Hugonot.</hi> There remains only the firſt point,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:66400:24"/>which ought not to laſt long accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to all appearances. Thus all the other Decrees that have been made againſt them does only retrench the Branches; but theſe cut up the very roots. Which may make them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend that their ruin is directly and ſpeedily aimed at.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>And I aſſure you they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly comprehend it; and thoſe I have ſeen, ſeem to me extreamly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm'd. But I know not if you are acquainted that there are ſeveral Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks who are much diſcontented, and ſay, We will be Catholicks out of Conſcience, and not out of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint. What! the Inquiſition is brought upon us, we are depriv'd of that Liberty of Conſcience, that is the moſt precious thing in the World: If we were ſo unhappy as to be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken, and fall into Hereſie; the King, would he ſave our Souls with detaining us by force in the Catholick Church? We ſhould be damned not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the King; as well in quality of concealed Hereticks, as in quality of Hypocrites. Beſides, the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:66400:25"/>King will thereby loſe all thoſe of his Subjects, who would change Religion. It will not be difficult for a Catholick, who will turn <hi>Hugonot,</hi> to diſpoſe of his Goods before he declares, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards to into a Forreign Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>Beſides, theſe extraordinary means, which are made uſe of to Convert them, there are a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of others which make leſs noiſe, that are Employed however with great ſucceſs: As much miſchief is done them as can be; they are depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of all means of gaining their live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood: They are not allowed to be of Arts and Trades; though the Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and Edicts expreſly bear they ſhall be received into them. Injuſtice is done them; they are drove from moſt part of the Bars; they are not allowed to be of a Body of Phiſicians, they are offered Money, and ſums are put into the Hands of the principal Judges and Governours to be diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the Converted: Thoſe have it by advance, who promiſe to turn. When by all theſe means they have
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:66400:25"/>been induced to change Religion, the Declaration againſt Relapſes fixes them in ſuch a manner, that they dare not return to their firſt Religion, though their Conſciences often ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit them to it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I hear them particularly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of the ills their Miniſters ſuffer: They ſay that people are ſent to hear their Sermons; that theſe ignorant and faithleſs people, impute to them things they never ſaid, and even make Crimes of the moſt innocent expreſſions: Whereupon their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are troubled, are put into Priſon, are condemned to ſome ſhameful ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, and to unſay it in open Seſſions; ſome to be drawn upon Sledges with the Executioner, others to be baniſhed, others to ſuffer Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcation, and the loſs of all their Goods. It is but ſome few years ſince that the Priſons in the Province of <hi>Poictou,</hi> were all full of their Miniſters, and their Ancients, becauſe they had preached upon the ruines of the Temples that had been deſtroyed.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:66400:26"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>Do you find this ſtrange? Is it not the Miniſters who keep them in their errour? In fleecing theſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and driving them away, by the troubles they are put to, their flocks will be no longer inſtructed in their Religion, and will be eaſily reduced to the Catholick Religion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>But to the purpoſe. Have not you heard talk of what has been done againſt the Miniſters in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Xaintonge,</hi> by the Lieutenant General of <hi>Xaintes?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, the buſineſs has come to our Ears: You ſee that all the world is let looſe upon them. All is permitted, provided it tends to do them miſchief. Neither does the Court any longer make a Myſtery of the hatred it has, and is deſirous the people ſhould have for them. You may have obſerved in the Declaration which forbids Catholicks to turn <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonots,</hi> that the King is made to ſay, that the liberty of Conſcience which had been granted to the pretended Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, had augmented the hatred that the Catholicks had againſt their perſons and their Religion.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:66400:26"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I avow to you that that part ſuprized me. In all the other De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations it was always ſaid that the deſign of the Edicts was to eſtabliſh peace between the Subjects of one and the other Religion; and the Kings have ever commanded an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and good intelligence between them. But it is at preſent clear that theſe people are abandoned to the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and fury of the Catholick people. The King is too good and too wiſe to have cauſed this Clauſe to be inſerted, he was certainly ſurprized; but let us return to the affair of <hi>Xaintonge.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>Thus then it was. The Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Lieutenant of <hi>Xaintes</hi> cauſed a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt to be preſented him by the Kings Sollicitor of that place, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding that the Miniſters might be held to the obſervation of the eleventh Article of <hi>Charles</hi> the Ninth's Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, of the 17th of <hi>January,</hi> 1561. Thus run the terms of the Article; The Miniſters ſhall be obliged to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before our Officers of Places, and take Oath of the obſervation of theſe Preſents, and promiſe not to preach
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:66400:27"/>any Doctrine which is contrary to the pure Word of God, as it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Symbol of the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> and in the Canonique Books of the Old and New Teſtaments, that our Subjects may not be filled with new Hereſies. According to this Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, the Lieutenant-General of <hi>Xaintes</hi> has ordered that the Miniſters of his Province ſhould be obliged to make Oath before him; and upon refuſal he has forbidden them all Function of their Miniſtry to the very viſiting the Sick. To which ſeveral have impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſubmitted: for it was very ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie for them to have gone on and not have obeyed, becauſe it belongs on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the King and his Intendants of Juſtice to ſilence Miniſters.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>But why do the <hi>Hugonot</hi> Miniſters make a difficulty of taking the Oath?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe that under pretext of the Oath, that they ſhould have taken, of preaching nothing contrary to the Word of God, they might have been hindred from preaching againſt the Catholick Religion: You know ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:66400:27"/>well that the points which ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Us from the <hi>Hugonots</hi> are in the Word of God, and all our Doctors prove them by Scripture, as well as by the Fathers, and by Reaſon. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, by this means a Declaration was revived that is not favourable to them, which was extinguiſhed above an Age ago, and which was likewiſe never executed. In reviving one Article of it all the others were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived: and likewiſe by renewing this Declaration, they would have a right of recalling alſo all the others which were much more favourable to them. They ſtill add, that it doth not belong to a little particular Judge to aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate their Yoke; that they live un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the Priviledge of the Kings Edicts, and that the King is their only Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in things that concern Religion. But I muſt acquaint you with what has been imagined againſt them in <hi>Brittany,</hi> which is well worth that of <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aintonge.</hi> A Curate bethought himſelf to give out a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> pain of Excommunication for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                        <desc>•••…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging his Pariſhioners to reveal all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> who had ſpoken irreverently of the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:66400:28"/>Catholick Religion. There was a prodigious number of Witneſſes, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther falſe or true found; who depoſed againſt the <hi>Hugonots</hi> of thoſe parts: Inſomuch that they were all obliged to fly to avoid Impriſonment. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the place is called <hi>Quiatin;</hi> it is a Lordſhip which belongs to the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the <hi>Mouſſays.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>This Affair of <hi>Britany,</hi> as well as that of <hi>Xaintonge</hi> brings into my mind another of Dauphine, which has this in Common with thoſe, as to make appear that generally all that is done againſt thoſe people comes from the ſame principle that we have already enough remarked; that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is ſpared, even to believe that it is a work grateful to God, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute to them falſe Crimes for the caſting them into certain ruin: But perhaps you know the Story as well as I; it is what paſſed ſome years ſince in the purſuit of the Recollects of <hi>Nions,</hi> have you not heard of it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>Being one day by chance at the late Chancellour <hi>N</hi>'s Houſe, I heard them talk of a Bell, that the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:66400:28"/>would have taken from the <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonots</hi> of that place, and I alſo remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that they made ſo much noiſe with their Bell, that the Counſel was ſtun'd: But I know nothing more of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>What I am going to relate to you, has made much more noiſe than the Bell of <hi>Nions.</hi> It came into thoſe good Fathers Heads that the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of <hi>Vinſobres,</hi> a ſmall neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Village of their Convent, kept ſecret Correſpondence with the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh:</hi> They ſo well repreſented this idle imagination to the Kings Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney General of that Province, that he immediately declared himſelf his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſer. The whole Parliament of <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble</hi> ſell into this Snare; one of the moſt able Counſellors of their Body, was deputed Commiſſioner to inform inceſſantly upon the Places, The Grand Provoſt took the Field with him, followed by all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Serjeants, the Sieur <hi>B</hi>— (thus is the Miniſters Name) chooſing rather to be a Bird of the Forreſt than the Cage, frighted at their March, fled as ſoon as he had notice of it. His
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:66400:29"/>Evaſion fortified the ſuſpicions that were given them of him. They fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>l the Syndio of the Conſiſtory might likewiſe be of the Party, and that the Miniſter had done nothing without his Participation. He was the Cock of the Pariſh, and a man likewiſe very well to paſs, who at all adventures could pay the Fidlers. His perſon was ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d without other form of Proceſs. He was conducted with Irons upon his Hands and Legs into the Conciergery of the Palace. The people cryed every where againſt him all along the way. He was to have been ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap>ed alive at leaſt and they ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap>ck'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> all parts to <hi>Grenoble</hi> to ſee the Execution; but in fine, <hi>Parturiunt Montes exit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Mus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>How! Did it all go into ſmoke?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>Even ſo: After they had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined the buſineſs, there was found nothing in it, and thoſe that had been concerned were the Publick laughter. The truth is, that the Parliament, in ſome manner to ſave their honour, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained this Syndie two whole years
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:66400:29"/>in Priſon; but that time being expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, he was releaſed, without being condemned or abſolved. The Door was opened to him one day when he leaſt expected it. And all the Fruit that was gathered from this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Proceſs was that this good man turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Catholick during his detention.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>This is puſhing the zeal of Religion very far, and becoming ſtrangely ridiculous. What likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood is there, that in <hi>Dauphine,</hi> which is the fartheſt Province of <hi>France</hi> from <hi>England,</hi> they ſhould undertake to keep Intelligence with <hi>England,</hi> while that in <hi>Guyenne</hi> and in <hi>Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> which are its Neighbours, they had no thoughts of it? Neither can I conceive how that a Miniſter of a Village can be bold enough to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, and able enough to carry on an Affair of that importance. But were not theſe Recollects puniſhed for their falſe Accuſation?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>They had no great thanks for having occaſioned this Sally; but what is to be done with people of the <hi>Frocks?</hi> Their Excuſe was their
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:66400:30"/>good intentions, and they were freed with a ſmall Reprimand<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that the Chief Preſident <hi>de la Berchere</hi> made them, who is certainly a Magiſtrate of the greateſt Integrity, and one of the beſt Servants the King has in <hi>France.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>And what became of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, was not he Condemned out of Contumacy?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov,</speaker>
                  <p>Very far from that, he was ſuffered to take away his Goods, an account of which had been taken, and would have returned to his Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, if that Tempeſt had not drove him into a good Port in <hi>Swizzerland.</hi> He poſſeſſes a Poſt incomparably better than that of <hi>Vinſobres;</hi> and theſe Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Fathers have procured him Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and Repoſe, without thinking on it. Within theſe two years another Miniſter of the ſame Province has done as much. The Religious of St. <hi>Anthony</hi> of <hi>Vienois</hi> perſecuted him, he retired into <hi>Holland,</hi> where he was very well received.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>Is it not the Miniſter of—who was ſeen rouling a long
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:66400:30"/>time at St. <hi>Germains</hi> and <hi>Verſeilles,</hi> after the Courts <hi>Taile?</hi> I have heard it confuſedly ſaid, that he was accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of Treaſon, and detained ſeveral Months in Priſon; but that he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged himſelf, and yet was ſilenced by a decree of the Parliament of <hi>Greneble.</hi> I know nothing of the particulars of his buſineſs, if you are informed of them, I pray you tell me what they are.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>You have divined him, it is the ſame; his adventure has ſomething very ſingular. The <hi>Hugo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nots</hi> of <hi>Dauthine</hi> had kept a Faſt in all their Churches; and the Synod that had ordered it, had enjoyned all the Miniſters that belonged to it, aſſiſted with their Ancients<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to viſit Families, and put them in mind of what had been promiſed God on the Faſt day. Theſe are the terms of the Article, which was Printed and Divulged. This Miniſter did not fail to execute this Order in his Diſtrict. It was during the heat of the War with <hi>Holland:</hi> The Religious of St. <hi>Anthony,</hi> who had lain in wait for him a long time,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:66400:31"/>laid hold on this occaſion, to inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate themſelves with the Court, to his Coſt. They writ to <hi>M. le Tellier</hi> then Secretary of State, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was contriving againſt the Kings Service; that the <hi>Hugonots</hi> had celebrated a Faſt through all <hi>Dauphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate;</hi> that there was a Plot Couch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under this Faſt, and that Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was only the pretext of it: That the Miniſter of—had held ſecret Aſſemblies at the Houſes of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipals of his Pariſh; that he had pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed God for the ſucceſs of the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> Arms, and that he had gathered great ſums of Money from thoſe of of his Party to ſend to the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>Good! Could this come into rational Heads? though all the <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonots</hi> of the Kingdom ſhould have contributed to this gathering, it would not have been ſufficient to have furniſhed Oats to the Cavallry of the Army the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded: They can hardly maintain the ſix or ſeven hundred Miniſters they have, ſince the Seal and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venſion
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:66400:31"/>Moneys were taken from them, that were deſtined to that uſe, without any thinking of gatherings for forreign Countries.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I knew very well you would alſo cry out upon this. Yet as ſtrange and as unlikely as the thing is, it cauſed this Miniſter a great deal of trouble: There came Orders from the King to ſeize his Perſon. He was kept in Priſon for above four Months, falſe Witneſſes were raiſed to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Accuſation, and if he had not had the Addreſs to Convince them in the Confrontation, he would certainly have paſſed his time very ill.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>This is horrible! It is rather fury than zeal. But it is with our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious as with Angels, when they are Corrupted, they are Devils. There is no manner of ill, but what they are capable of. Thoſe of St. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony</hi> ſurpaſs in this all the other Or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ders. They have appropriated to themſelves vaſt Riches of St. <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> under pretext of Serving the ſick. Monſieur <hi>de Louvois,</hi> who is
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:66400:32"/>chief of this Order, deſigns to make them reſtore theſe Goods, and to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply them to the Hall of <hi>Mars,</hi> deſtined to the maintenance of the maimed, without doubt theſe Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to fence off this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, with which they were threatned and to inſinuate themſelves into the Kings favour, bethought themſelves of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving this advice to the Court, and ſacrificing this Miniſter to their Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>You have hit the mark, and methinks ſo many Monks ought not to be ſuffered. The Policy of <hi>France</hi> obſerves there are too many. It would be convenient to retrench at leaſt the two thirds of them, and to apply the Revenues of their Houſes, which are immenſe, to the neceſſities of the State, and to the eaſe of the people. And the other Thirds Wings ought likewiſe to be clipped, and hindred from growing great, by forbidding them, as is done at <hi>Venice,</hi> to acquire ſtocks and receive conſiderable Gifts and Legacies. It is the ſame with their Fraternities as with the Den of <hi>Eſops</hi> Lyon, all goes in
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:66400:32"/>and nothing comes out, and it is not otherwiſe poſſible, but that at length they muſt become yet more powerful and formidable.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>I am impatient to know the iſſue of this Proceſs, I beg you would tell it me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>The falſe Witneſſes were freed for a Years abſence from the Province, and the Religious for ſome Reprimands from the Judges. As for the Miniſter, he was fined without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Note of Infamy, and condemned to pay the Charges, by reaſon of the viſits he had made, which they called Aſſemblies, and the ſilencing of his Miniſtry too, happy to have thus eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped from the Snare that was laid him. I ſaw the Sentence in Print, and fixed up by Order of the Bench. You ſee by all theſe Stories that all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ways are tryed for the tiring out thoſe people; their ruin comes on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pace; conſider how many Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons there be againſt them, within theſe two Years.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>Two things are the cauſe of this. The firſt is the Peace; while the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:66400:33"/>King has leſs forreign Affairs he em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploys himſelf in the reforming the diſorders that may be in the State, and in the Religion. Moreover the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputes the King has had with the Pope, has obliged him to appear ſevere againſt the <hi>Hugonots.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>What <hi>Mozeray</hi> has obſerved in the Life of <hi>Henry</hi> the 2d, is very true, that the diſputes of the Kings of <hi>France</hi> with the Popes, have ever coſt the <hi>Hugonots</hi> dear. As ſoon as a Prince thinks of defending himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the enterprizes of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> he is accuſed of being an Abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of Hereſie; and Princes to clear themſelves of this ſuſpicion redouble their ſeverity againſt the Hereticks.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſee that the Pope, in the Briefs he has written to the King, praiſes him for his zeal againſt Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and gives him joy for having de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed ſo many Temples; and the King on his part, to appeaſe the Pope, has not failed to make him obſerve, that in few Weeks he has made three very ſtrong Declarations againſt the <hi>Hugonots.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:66400:33"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>Since we are fallen upon this, tell me in ſhort, what were the diſputes the King had with the Pope?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>There were two, The firſt was upon the account of the Regali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and the ſecond upon the account of the <hi>Urbaniſts.</hi> The Regality is a Right our Kings have over vacant Biſhopricks, upon the Deceaſe, or the Demiſſion of thoſe who poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them. During the vacancy, the Fruits of them belong to the King; and even till that the new Biſhop has taken the Oath of Fidelity in Perſon, all the Benifices which would be at the Biſhops Nomination, are at the Kings. The moſt part of the Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks in <hi>France</hi> have ſubmitted to this Right. However there are ſome who pretend not to be in the Regali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and, amongſt others, thoſe of <hi>Guyenne</hi> and <hi>Languedock.</hi> Of which kind is the Biſhoprick of <hi>Pamiers</hi> near the <hi>Pyrences.</hi> The King pretended he had the Right of Regality over that Biſhoprick; the Biſhop pretended not His Temporals were ſeized on, of which he complained to the Pope,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:66400:34"/>who proceeded ſo far in this affair, as to threaten the King to make uſe of the Arms of the Church againſt him. The <hi>Urbaniſts</hi> are the Maidens of S. <hi>Clair,</hi> whoſe Rule was mitigated by Pope <hi>Urban</hi> the 5th. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have retained the Name of <hi>Ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baniſts.</hi> Theſe Maidens had kept the Right of Electing Superiours, and Regular Abbeſſes, according to the Canons: The King on the contrary pretended he had the Right of Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to theſe Abbeys, as well as to all the other Great Benefices. The Biſhop of <hi>Pamiers</hi> maintained the Rights of theſe Maidens, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged the Pope to maintain it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>This Biſhop of <hi>Pamiers</hi> ſeems to me a terrible man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>He is dead; but I aſſure you he was an honeſt man: He was for the Obſervation of the ancient Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons; and if he might have been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, he would have re-eſtabliſhed the vigour of the ancient Diſcipline. Not that his own Genius of it ſelf was proper to maintain a great affair: But he was an Admirer of <hi>M. d' Alet,</hi>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:66400:34"/>who was one of the Chief men of the Age for Purity of manners, and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of Diſcipline. The Biſhop of <hi>Pamiers</hi> did nothing but by his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and followed all his Maximes; he has ever followed them, even ſince the Death of <hi>M. d' Alet.</hi> They were both moſt zealous <hi>Janſeniſts.</hi> You know the great troubles they have had about ſigning the Formulary, which they ſo long reſiſted: They were both great Enemies of the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, and of varying from Morality. Wherefore Father <hi>le Cheiſe,</hi> a Jeſuit, who governed the Kings Conſcience, was not ſorry to find an occaſion to revenge his party, and he perſwaded the King as much as was poſſible to vex this good Biſhop, who was likewiſe a declared Enemy of the Court Biſhops: which brought upon his back the Archbiſhop of <hi>Paris.</hi> For perhaps you know that this Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop is the Original, of whom a little Book intituled, the Court Biſhop, is the Copy. Some fancied it was the Biſhop of <hi>Amiens,</hi> whom the Author principally aimed at, but this is a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake;
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:66400:35"/>it was the Archbiſhop of <hi>Rou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en,</hi> who had been Biſhop of <hi>Seer,</hi> and who is at preſent Archbiſhop of <hi>Paris.</hi> The Author of this little Book that has made ſo much noiſe in the World, and that has ſo much enraged my Lords the Biſhops, is one called <hi>le Noir,</hi> and has been Arch-Deacon of the Church of <hi>Seer.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>But do you not look upon it as a very ſingular thing, that at preſent the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> favours the <hi>Janſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> againſt the <hi>Jeſuits?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>It is what never would have been foreſeen: for the intereſts of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and thoſe of the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits</hi> have been ſo interwoven, that they were believed inſeparable. The <hi>Jeſuits</hi> make a fourth Vow to the Pope: they carry his Authority as far as it it can go: they place him both above Councils, and above all Kings, as well in Temporals as in Spirituals; and therein paſs to ſuch exceſſes as the other Catholicks do not approve. The Court at <hi>Rome</hi> for its part has regards for them that it has not for any other Order. But it appears that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:66400:35"/>Pope is favourable to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> upon Grace. He is eſpecially a great Enemy of thoſe varyings from Morality, of which the Jeſuits are the principal Authors. He has cauſed a Bull to be publiſhed which Condemns 65 Propoſitions of this looſe Morality.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>Good God! But I am ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalized, that this Bull was not received in <hi>France;</hi> and that it was forbidden by an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I know very well the pretext; which is, That the Bull iſſued from the Tribunal of the Inquiſition, which is not acknowledged in <hi>France.</hi> But, in fine, an expedient might have been found not to have ſcandalized a whole Nation. Who would not imagine that the deteſtable Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are approved of, which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by this Bull, ſince that the Publication of the Bull is forbidden?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>Certainly the Credit of Father <hi>le Cheiſe,</hi> and the Jeſuit Party, has appeared therein. And this goes much farther than you think of; for in the firſt minute of the Declaration,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:66400:36"/>theſe words were put, Though that theſe propoſitions are juſtly condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; Father <hi>le Cheiſe</hi> has cauſed theſe words to be raiſed out, and has put in their ſtead, That even the good things which come to us from the Tribunal of the Inquiſition ought not to be received.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>But what do you think of the preſent Pope?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>For my part I believe he is the honeſteſt of all the Church-men. The Holy See has not for a long time been poſſeſſed by a Perſon of ſo great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bity: He is perfectly of an Apoſtolick Character.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I have ſeen <hi>Hugonots</hi> who had an eſteem for him, and who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved him capable of indeavouring a good Reformation, if he was aided and followed; but he has every where found a ſurprizing oppoſition. The Bull he has publiſhed againſt ſome In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences was ſo ill received in <hi>France,</hi> that all good Souls have been ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized. The King is made to ſay upon the Subject of this Bull, that the Pope had newly done more hurt to the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:66400:36"/>Church than the <hi>Hugonots</hi> could do it in fifty Years.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>There is however one thing in this good Pope, that I cannot ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of, which is, that he will not bate any thing of thoſe high and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perb pretenſions of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> touching the infallibility of the Holy See, and the ſuperiority of the Pope over the Temporals of Kings. You perhaps know that he has cauſed to be put into the expurgatory Index, by the Congregation of the Inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the lives of Father <hi>Maimbourg,</hi> and amongſt others the Hiſtory of the fall of the Empire, becauſe there were found therein ſome Propoſitions that were not conformable enough to the <hi>Italian</hi> Theology, and which render<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Princes too Independant on the Pope in Temporals. Methinks that a Pope of his Character ought to have humility, and by conſequence ought not to entertain the haughty ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his Predeceſſours, who brought down Crowned Heads under their feet.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:66400:37"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>What you tell me I was igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of. This is very ſingular, a Jeſuite cry out againſt the Pope. Ah! without doubt it is to revenge the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of the Jeſuites, and puniſh the Pope for favouring their Enemies. Theſe Gentlemen know how to ſay, God ſave the King, and the ſame of the League, according to Junctures.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>The hatred certainly of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Maimbourg</hi> againſt the <hi>Janſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts,</hi> might well oblige him to write after a contrary manner to the Popes intereſts; for this Father is one of the greateſt Enemies of Port-Royal. But beſides that the Glory of the King, and the great Succeſs of his Armes, engages that Society into this Conduct; one would ſay that Father <hi>Maimbourg</hi> delights and is proud to ſee his Books in the Index, and that he had compoſed his Hiſtory of <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raniſme</hi> on purpoſe to enlarge the Catalogue of forbidden Books at <hi>Rome;</hi> for he loſes not any occaſion of cenſuring the Popes Conduct; and has likewiſe found the means of doing one to the purpoſe, in his Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:66400:37"/>of <hi>Luther,</hi> for to Condemn the ſentiments and actions of the preſent Pope, upon the diſpute he had with the King about the Regality. In the bottom the Jeſuits have not abandon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Theology: They are as zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous <hi>Partizans</hi> of the Holy See, as they have ever been, but they diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and tollerate Father <hi>Maimbourg,</hi> becauſe he flatters a Prince whom they are afraid to offend. The King is very jealous of his Authority and his grandeur; he is glad to find peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple who maintain the right of Kings againſt the pretenſions of the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi> He flatters the Jeſuites ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much, he lets Father <hi>le Cheiſe</hi> reign, who is of that Order; it is juſt they have ſome Complaiſance for him. But in the bottom they diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vow Father <hi>Maimbourg,</hi> and in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reign he would not have eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for an eaſie Diſcipline. Father <hi>le Cheiſe</hi> is likewiſe as much out with the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> as one can be; wherefore it is his intereſt to mannage the Kings mind, without whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection he cannot ſtand; and it is he
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:66400:38"/>who upholds Father <hi>Maimbourg.</hi> In the mean time the Protectours of the Liberties of the <hi>Gallicane</hi> Church pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, that this Father does a great deal of honour to his Society, and that he makes appear that the <hi>Italian</hi> Theology, touching the Popes Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, does not paſs amongſt the Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites for an Article of Faith, as was hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto believed; but for the reaſons I have told you, I do not think that a great advantage can be drawn from it. The General of the Jeſuites has very nearly explain'd himſelf therein. The Pope having made great complaints to him of Father <hi>le Cheiſe,</hi> and of Father <hi>Maimbourg;</hi> he anſwered, he could do nothing againſt two perſons who were under the Protection of ſo great a King; that is to ſay, That if the Times, or the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment changed, the Pope ſhould have ſatisfaction for the Enterprizes of thoſe two Jeſuits.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I am ſurprized that the Pope, of the Character I fancy him, is ſo jealous of that falſe Authority that his Predeceſſors have uſurped over the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:66400:38"/>Church, and over Kings; and I am the more aſtoniſhed at it, for that the Book of the Biſhop of <hi>Condom</hi> had perſuaded me, that the Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies concerning the Popes Authority were no longer conſidered at <hi>Rome</hi> as Affairs of importance. You know that in that work, he paſſes very lightly over the Popes Authority, and ſays only general things, which all Catholicks agree to. I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways that little Book about me, let us ſee what it is. As to things which are known to be diſputed of in the Schools, though Miniſters do not ceaſe to alledge them for the ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring that Power odious, it is not neceſſary to ſpeak of them, ſince they are not of the Catholick Faith. It is ſufficient to acknowledge a Head e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed by God for the guiding his flock in his ways. This ſignifies clearly enough, that all that is ſaid to exceſs concerning the Popes Authority by the Monks and <hi>Italians,</hi> ought to be reckoned as nothing. And you ſee how all the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves this Book; and there is even
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:66400:39"/>a Brief of the Pope, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends both its Method and Doctrine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>What you ſay is like an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Country-man, and one real. How came you to fall into this Snare? Could you believe that the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> would renounce thoſe pretended <hi>Rights</hi> which have coſt it ſo much trouble, and even blood to acquire! believe me, the pleaſure of reigning is too ſweet to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce it. This Empire that the Pope ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes over the Kings of Chriſtendom raiſes him too high to abandon it. The truth is, that ſome Princes, in imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> indeavour to caſt off the Yokes. The Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours are no longer Crowned by the Pope; the <hi>Vatican</hi> Thunderbolts are no longer ſo formidable. The Kings of <hi>Portugal</hi> have not abandoned their Crown, though the Popes would take it from them. But be it as it will; though the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould have loſt the Body of that Power, it would keep the Shaddow to the laſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>So that this pretended yiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> upon the point of its Authority, is a ſnare laid for the <hi>P.</hi> Reformed.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:66400:39"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>You may judge by the delica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of that Court, in regard of the Writings of Father <hi>Maimbourg:</hi> For in fine, this Father has written after a very reſpectful manner for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly See; yet it is imputed to him as a Crime, that he has not uttered matters as the other Writers of his Society.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>Since we are upon the Book of <hi>M. de Condom;</hi> I muſt ask your Opinion of it. You promiſed to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint me with all the means by which they pretend to reduce the <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonots</hi> ſuddenly to the Boſom of the Church, and you tell me nothing of thoſe mild ways ſo much talked of, and which are looked upon as ſure means to Convert all thoſe of that Party, who are neither obſtinate nor prejudiced.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>Nothing can be more witty, better turned, and more delicate than the Book of <hi>M. de Condom:</hi> But I ſaid nothing of it to you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I do not believe it uſeful for the guiding to what it tends. In the bottom that method is worth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:66400:40"/>and in the ſequel will do more hurt to the Catholick Church, than it does it good at preſent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſee, however, that ſeveral perſons who read that Work ſpeak of it as a Maſter-piece; and I have ſeen ſeveral <hi>Hugonots</hi> whom that Book has Converted.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>Believe me, dear Sir, that thoſe people would have been Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted without the Book of <hi>M. de Condom.</hi> This Book only Converts thoſe who were willing to abandon their Religion, and who ſeek for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text to defend themſelves againſt the Accuſation of lightneſs. The late <hi>M. de Turene</hi> was the firſt who took a great deal of pains to raiſe the val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of that Action. He turned Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick after having grown gray in the <hi>Hugonot</hi> Party. He feared to be accuſed of having quitted his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on out of Intereſt. As he was extream nice upon the point of honour, and that Glory was his Idol, he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to perſuade all the Earth that he turned out of a principle of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. From a Convert he even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:66400:40"/>a Convertor; and becauſe that he could not be perſuaded that ſeveral things that are taught and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed amongſt us were good, he was glad to meet with <hi>Abbe Boſſuit,</hi> who turned things as he would have them, and who diſguiſed what he could not look upon without a diſguiſe. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the world became Charmed with this piece, and it was reported that it made ſeveral Converts. Several <hi>Hugonots</hi> got themſelves inſtructed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that Method, they were glad they could ſay that their Miniſters were notorious Libellers, having repreſented to them the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> wholly diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from what it is. The fame of this Book paſſed into <hi>Italy:</hi> The Court of <hi>Rome</hi> was perſuaded all <hi>France</hi> would become Catholicks, and fall into this ſnare. But the truth is, that Book is only good to cauſe Relapſes. For if the <hi>Hugonots</hi> were really Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted upon the aſſurances that this Book gave them, that we do not ſerve Images, and invoke Saints, but as we pray the Faithful upon the Earth,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:66400:41"/>to beſeech God in our behalf; what would they ſay, when they came into our Churches, and that they ſaw there the Images Served, and the Saints invoqued by all the external acts of a Religious adoration? They would certainly cry out upon us, for having deceived them, and would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the ſink of Hereſie. It would be better to act Faithfully, tell things as they are, and make known to Hereticks the naked truth. But I avow to you this is not the greateſt miſchief this Book may do.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>What is that ſo terrible miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief which you foreſee, and which makes you ſo afraid?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>That miſchief is, that ſuch Books are capable of multiplying a Party that is in the boſome of the Catholick Church, and which will one day be its ruin, if care be not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. You muſt know then, that the Church had never ſo many ill Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks as it has at preſent. The Town, Country, Court, and Armies are full of Deiſts, a ſort of people who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that all Religions are the inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:66400:41"/>of humane Wit. Theſe raſh Heads doubt of all; they are armed with wicked difficulties, againſt the Books of the Old and New Teſtament, that they may not be obliged to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that thoſe Books were really written by the Authors whoſe Names they bear. From hence it proceeds, that ſuch as pretend to any Capacity in writing, have bethought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of defending the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion againſt the incredulous; all their works turn that way; and thus if a <hi>Bedunt</hi> makes a Collection of Scraps and Criticiſme upon the Books of the Old and New Teſtament, or upon ſome particular Texts, he calls that Evangelical Demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Reflections upon the Truth of the Chriſtian Religion. And the moſt part of theſe Collections, are fitter to confirm theſe Deiſts in their increduli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, than to make them return; becauſe ſuch Compilations are not regulated by Judgment: What's good is mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with what's ill, and force with weakneſs; and thoſe incredulous minds are the more confirmed in this
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:66400:42"/>incredulity, by the ill reaſons and weak Conjectures that are given them for ſolid Remarks, and are not touched with the good Reaſons that are mingled with the ill. Beſides, ſuch kind of Works, wherein are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated a hundred ſeveral Opinions up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one and the ſame Subject; do but furniſh a new pretext to their incredu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity: They conclude that all is uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; that the moſt enlightned knew not what to hold to, and whoſe Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions were quite contrary. The truth is, that ſome of theſe Writings that are made for the defence of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, are of a Bulk to fright thoſe Libertines, who are not capable of a long Application: Thus never reading thoſe great Volumes, they do not draw Concluſions diſadvanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous to the Chriſtian Religion. But as for Books of the ſize of that of <hi>M. de Condoms,</hi> all the world reads them. Now you cannot believe how much the Method thoſe Gentlemen make uſe of, who have invented theſe gentle ways, confirms theſe Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertines in their ſentiments. Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:66400:42"/>is therein repreſented to them with a Face wholly new; and thereupon they tell us, here is a man who tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſports us into another Country: In this new Religion Images are not made uſe of, Saints are not invoqued, they are only prayed to, as we pray the faithful upon the Earth to beſeech God in our Regard. I had hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to believed that the Devotions for the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and for the other Saints, were things of importance: I ſee that moſt part of the Devout lay great ſtreſs upon theſe things; and yet theſe ſay that they are nothing, that they may be let a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and that it is ſufficient to invoke God and Jeſus Chriſt; they evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give ground; they acknowledge that the Church has erred, and that it is in the wrong to recommend the Service of Images and the invocation of Saints upon pain of <hi>Anathema.</hi> If the Church has erred in thoſe Articles, why ſhould it be infallible in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? It was miſtaken, when it or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered us to adore Images, build Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, inſtitute Feaſts, and make Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:66400:43"/>to the honour of Saints; and why may it not likewiſe have been mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken in that it has given us for Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, a Book which perhaps is not ſo? It has no other ſurety to give us for the truth of thoſe Books, and of that Religion which is founded upon thoſe Books, than its Authority and infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility; here are Catholick Authors, who evidently make a breach in that infallible Authority; and thus they open the door to all our Doubts.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I underſtand you. But is this the Party you think capable of ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ining the Catholick Religion?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>No: Theſe are not our moſt dangerous Enemies: They are ſuch Catholicks, as I call the third Party, who make profeſſion of believing that the <hi>Roman</hi> Church is the true Church, that we ought to be inſeparably fixed in it, and that we ought never to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from it, but who, however, do not act as it commands, nor have any reſpect for its Worſhip. Theſe ſort of people were never ſo nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous as they are now in this Kingdom. There be ſome amongſt them who
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:66400:43"/>puſh their incredulity ſo far, as to doubt of the moſt important truths of Chriſtianity. They are <hi>Socinians,</hi> they neither believe the Myſtery of the Trinity, nor that of the Incarnation. I know ſuch particular inſtances, that I do not doubt thereof. I ſhall not tell you them, becauſe they would only help to make you abhor them. And what is moſt terrible is, that it is not only the Religion of our young Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bots, it is the Divinity of ſome grave and wiſe Societies, and who make parade of the purity of their manners, and of their zeal for the Catholick Faith. Judge you whether ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as doubt of the myſteries of the Trinity, and the Incarnation, which all Chriſtians receive, have reſpect for that of the Real Preſence and of Tranſubſtantiation, which has been expoſed to ſo many Contradictions within theſe ſeven or eight hundred years? Without reckoning theſe <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians,</hi> it is certain that ſeveral Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks are in no manner perſuaded of the truth of this Myſtery; neither do they make any difficulty of open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:66400:44"/>themſelves to the Enemies of our Religion, when they are one to one, and that they cannot be troubled for it. When they are asked how they can adore an Object which they only look upon as a Creature? they ſay, that they do not adore the Sacrament, but that their adoration has reſpect to Jeſus Chriſt, who is ſeated in the Heavens upon the Throne of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>Not long ſince I happened to be in a place, where I was Witneſs of a very warm debate between Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, who accuſed certain new Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, of being very ill Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, and of being of Intelligence with the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> upon the point of the Euchariſt. Are not theſe the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple you ſpoke of?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes; at leaſt thoſe you menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are part of thoſe I ſpoke of; for there are ſeveral others, beſides theſe new Philoſophers, who have no faith for the myſteries of the Euchariſt. Thoſe new Philoſophers you ſpeak of are called <hi>Carteſians</hi> and <hi>Gaſſendiſts.</hi> I never much concerned my ſelf with
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:66400:44"/>thoſe Philoſophical diſputes; but I have heard them ſo often debated, that I remember ſome of them. I have often heard ſay, that theſe Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers believe, ſome that the Eſſence of the Matter and of Bodies conſiſts in the actual ſpace, and others that it conſiſts in the impenetrability. Thereupon the zealous Catholicks tell them that this Philoſophy ruins the myſtery of the Real Preſence; for if the Bodies are eſſentially extended, and impenetrable, it is impoſſible that the Body of Jeſus Chriſt can be in the Euchariſt without extent and penetracting it ſelf; that is to ſay, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing its parts thrown into one another. Now it is the Faith of the Church, that the Body of Jeſus Chriſt is in the Sacrament included under a point.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>This difficulty is ſenſible; it is not neceſſary to be a Philoſopher to comprehend it: What anſwer do they make to it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>They reply to it by great proteſtations of the purity of their Faith, and of their Submiſſion to the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:66400:45"/>Church; they ſay that they ſpeak thereof as Philoſophers, and not as Divines; that they conſider Matter in its natural ſtate, when they define it by extent, or that they declare it to be eſſentially impenetrable; that they do not trouble themſelves with what it may be in its ſupernatural E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, wherein God can put it by his Power: They turn themſelves a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ways. Some ſay, that extent is the Eſſence of Bodies, but not ſuch an extent; that the Body of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Jeſus Chriſt had at the age of one Year, was the ſame Body that he had at the age of thirty Years: That the Body of Jeſus Chriſt may be in the Euchariſt, having only the greatneſs of a Hand-worm; and that this extent is ſufficient to ſave this truth, that the eſſence of Bodies conſiſts in extent. They likewiſe ſay, that the eſſence of the Body of Jeſus Chriſt conſiſts in a certain little part of the Brain, which is almoſt inſenſible, in which the Soul is fixed: And that by ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing that in the Euchariſt there is only that eſſential part of the Lords
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:66400:45"/>Body, he may be there Corporally without taking up much Room. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſay, that God deludes the Senſes, and that after the Conſecration, that which appears bread, is really the body of Jeſus Chriſt, that this Body of Jeſus Chriſt is extended; but that God by his Power cauſes this extent to remain inviſible; that bodies keep often their extent, and yet that exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is not to be perceived. When we ſee a Gyant from the top of a Mountain, he appears to us a Pigmy, yet he keeps all his bulk. In fine, they ſay ſuch ſtrange and improbable things, that it is clear that they themſelves are not at all perſuaded of them, and have no hopes of perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding others. In a word, being we cannot renounce Common ſenſe, nor believe that ſuch able men have loſt theirs, we cannot be perſuaded that they really believe Tranſubſtantiation poſſible. The misfortune is, that ſuch people as are engaged in theſe Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, are not ordinary men; but the moſt Illuſtrious Societies of the Church, and the pureſt, and the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:66400:46"/>chiefeſt Wits of the age. The Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of <hi>Port-Royal</hi> are men who have diſtinguiſhed themſelves as much as can be by their probity, by the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of their Morality and Divinity, by their ſolitary and retired way of living from the world, by their vaſt inlarged knowledge, by the penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Wit, by the beauty and fertility of their imagination, by the beauties they have inriched our Tongue with, and by Productions that are a great honour to <hi>France,</hi> and of great uſe to the Republick of Letters. All theſe ſo able men have as much Inclination for Carteſianiſme as for Chriſtianity. That great So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of the Fathers of Oratory have the ſame Principles. I know not whether you have heard talk of a Book called, <hi>The Search of Truth.</hi> This age has not produced a piece wherein there is more ſubtilty of argument, more penetration of Wit, and more ſolid Metaphyſicks. The Author of this Book, as well as all thoſe of his Society, ſeems to have a very great zeal for that Philoſophy. The truth
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:66400:46"/>is, that the Fathers of the Oratory have promiſed neither to ſpeak nor write thereof any more; but they have not promiſed not to think thereof; and as long as they ſhall think they cannot forbear communicating their thoughts. After all, this Method of hindring the teaching a Doctrine, is not ſo proper as is believed for the hindring its progreſs; eſpecially when Philoſophy is concerned, concerning which the Wits are perſuaded their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty ought not to be limitted: And we are the more violently inclined to things that are forbidden us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I have hearkned very atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively to all you have ſaid, and have well enough comprehended it; though it is not at all my Trade. But I do not underſtand what refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence all this has to the Book, of <hi>M. de Condom;</hi> and how this Book, which ſeems to have ſo much reſpect for the Myſtery of the Euchariſt, can ſerve to increaſe the Party of thoſe people who pretend to be the great wits, and who raiſe their reaſon againſt our Myſteries.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:66400:47"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>I will make you preſently comprehend it. All the Catholicks of the third Party, who have not too much reſpect for our Myſteries, have a profound Contempt for all popular Devotions. They look upon the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction of Images into Churches as a thing that might very well be laid aſide; the invocation of Saints as a ſuperfluity in the Worſhip, and is the Obſtacle to the re-union of all Chriſtians; and the Exceſſes that are committed in that invocation of Saints, as terrible ſuperſtitions that ſtain Religion: They blame the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Relicks, they laugh at all the Miracles that are made by Images. They ſay that Pilgrimages, Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Stations, the viſits of Priviledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches and Altars, Scapularies, Roſaries, Fraternities, are Monachal Devotions, and are only good to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the cheats of begging Monks. I my ſelf heard one of theſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſay, that the Doctrine of the Catholick Church was good, but that three parts of the Catholicks were Idolaters, by the abuſe that they
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:66400:47"/>made of the invocation of Saints, and the Service of Images. You are not ſuch a ſtranger in the world, as not to have heard talk of a little Book called, <hi>Salutary Advices of the bleſſed Virgin to her indiſcreet Votaries.</hi> This Book introduces the Virgin as ſpeaking, and condemning all the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions, and condemning all the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions, by which ſhe is uſually honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: The Biſhop of <hi>Tourney</hi> has made an Apology for this work, in his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoral Letter. Theſe Opinions have found more approvers in <hi>France</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our great Clergy than is cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible. But neither is it credible how much all the good and ſimple Souls amongſt the Catholicks have been ſcandalized at them. Theſe Libertine Writings have been refuted by other very Catholick Writings. Meſſire <hi>Lewis d' Abelly,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rhodez,</hi> and Father <hi>Craſſet</hi> the Jeſuite, have Learnedly and Solidly defended the Doctrine and Practice of the Church, in what concerns the honour that is done the Mother of God. But this does not hinder the contrary Party from increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, to the great ſcandal of all good
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:66400:48"/>Catholicks. Now it is certain, that nothing has more helped to augment that Party, than <hi>M. de Condom</hi>'s piece, which reduces the Service of Images to nothing, the invocaſion of Saints and veneration of Holy Relicks to ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little; ſpeaking very faintly of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences, ſaying nothing of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, and giving no great Idea of the Fruits of the Sacrifice of the Meſſias. It cannot be doubted, but that M. <hi>de Condom,</hi> and all the Divines of his Party, are of the ſame ſentiments with the Author of the Salutary Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of the bleſſed Virgin to her undi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcreet Votaries, and by Conſequence they look upon all Popular Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as great Superſtitions. Now cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly this is not edifying; it makes Hereticks Triumph, and helps to confirm them in their averſion to the Church. Though it ſhould happen, that the people and the Religious ſhould carry a little too far the hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and Service that are rendred to the Friends of God and his Mother, it would be better to diſſemble it, than to confeſs theſe exceſſes, and condemn
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:66400:48"/>them. Theſe Gentlemen are likewiſe ſo imprudent, as to bring to light ſuch ſcandalous Hiſtories as rejoice Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks. By example, can any thing be more terrible than what they have cauſed to be Printed againſt Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences and Relicks, with that Bull of Innocent the 11th. which condemns ſome ſuppoſed Relicks, without deſign of injuring thoſe that are real? Amongſt others, this is one of the Stories they have publiſhed; In the year 1668 Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the 4th ſent into <hi>France</hi> three Cheſts of Relicks, to be put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Hoſpital Church. Theſe three Cheſts were bound up with red ſilk Cords, and ſealed with the Seal of Cardinal <hi>Ginetti,</hi> Commiſſary for the Relicks, and with the Seal of the Popes <hi>Sacriſtain.</hi> Theſe Relicks were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with a Bull, which ſaid, that they might with all ſafety be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the veneration of the People. Magnificent Bills were ſet up in all parts to invite the People to this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion. The Biſhops of <hi>Bayeux,</hi> and <hi>Cahors,</hi> Father <hi>Don Coſme,</hi> Father <hi>Craſſot,</hi> and the Abbot <hi>Fromentieres,</hi>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:66400:49"/>were to preach during the <hi>Octave.</hi> It It was however ordered, they ſhould be ſearch'd. In the third Cheſt was found a Head, which at firſt appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be a real one: It had this Inſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, <hi>Caput Sancti Fortunati:</hi> In ſearching it, there was perceived above the ear a piece of painted Cloth: The Phyſician whoſe name was <hi>M. de Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main,</hi> took an Inſtrument, ſcraped it, and thruſt it in, and found it was a Paiſt-board Head. They put a lighted Candle into the Head, but the light did not penetrate; at laſt they caſt the Head into hot water, which took away the Paint, and the Paiſt-board fell in pieces. M. <hi>de St. Germain</hi> made his verbal Proceſs thereof; but by a ſealed Letter he was forbidden to ſhew it, upon pain of being ſent the ſame moment to the <hi>Baſtille.</hi> Is not it inſupportable, that Hereticks muſt learn ſuch like ſtories from Catholicks? and what kind of Catholicks are theſe? After all, theſe Catholicks of the third Party have paſſed by that bound of reſpect which was the ſafety of the Church;
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:66400:49"/>which is, the Opinion of its infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. It is impoſſible that ſuch people, as look upon with ſo much contempt the Devotions that the Church autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes, hold that Church for infallible. If they give the liberty of believing that it has err'd in ſome things, they will not ſtay to examine the reſt; and perhaps that their falſe Lights will car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry them much farther than they at preſent deſign to go. Thus I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that theſe mild ways, that are believed of ſo great uſe for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of Hereticks, may one day ruin the Church of <hi>France,</hi> and the Low Countries, if God and the Holy See do not take care in it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I am very well ſatisfied with having heard you, and you have learnt me ſeveral things that I was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to know. There remains ſome difficulties, touching the means that are to be made uſe of, for reducing <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonots</hi> to the Church; but I muſt take ſome time to think of thoſe diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, for the digeſting them, before I ask your inſtructions. Since to day is your weekly day of repoſe, be
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:66400:50"/>pleaſed, Sir, to come Dine with me at my Lodging this day ſeven night. VVe will there have a Room only for us two, and you ſhall make an end of informing me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>I willingly conſent to it, and ſhall not fail to be at the Rendezvous.</p>
               </sp>
               <trailer>The End of the Firſt Part.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="conference">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:66400:50"/>
               <head>THE POLICY OF THE <hi>CLERGY</hi> of <hi>FRANCE.</hi>
               </head>
               <head>The Second Conference.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>The Pariſian.</speaker>
                  <p>YOU ſee, Sir, how exact I am in keeping my word, I am only afraid I have made you wait too long. I had much a-do to get from a crowd of People who have troubled me all this Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>Perſons ſo agreeable to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany cannot be ſeen too much. But the Cook belonging to the Houſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:66400:51"/>your coming the more pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, for I fancy his Dinner is not yet ready.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Before Dinner they diſcourſe of the News of the Time, after Dinner the Converſation is thus renewed.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>Tell me, Sir, what you have done ſince I had the honour to ſee you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I have hardly done any thing, but I have ſuffered a great deal. In going from your Houſe I found at my Lodging a <hi>Hugonot</hi> Gentleman waiting for me; After ſome indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Converſations, I made him fall upon that of Religion, and was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to make uſe of the Counſel you had given me; that is to ſay, I mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him to quit his Religion, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the approaching ruine with which it is threatned. But, alas! I have extreamly repented I brought him upon that point, he has almoſt ſtunn'd me with Complaints and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. He is yet much more knowing than you in the particulars of the means that are employed for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:66400:51"/>his Party; ſince our Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence I have ſeen him daily, it being impoſſible for me to avoid him; for he was at my Bed-ſide before I was awake. Being a perſon of Quality, and diſtinguiſhing himſelf both by his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Riches, I durſt not order my <hi>Valet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> de Chambre</hi> to deny him en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance. Thus I have been obliged to ſuffer his perſecution, and give him audience three or four times every day.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>Good God! How could he find ſo many things to ſay upon one and the ſame point?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>He has repeated to me all that you told me, and has very much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged, by maintaining it with ſeveral ſtories that neither you nor I knew. He has ſhown me how much the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct that is held againſt their Party is contrary to Honeſty, Humanity, Good-faith, and even to the true In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the King and State. In ſine, I fancy a Book might be made of all he told me. Thus, far from convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, he had like to have pervert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:66400:52"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhould be glad to know ſome of the particulars of your Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I waited with great impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to impart them to you; for he has very much fortified the difficulty that I intend to propoſe to you. To ſpeak ſeriouſly, I muſt aſſure you, he ſometimes moved and touched me. For example, he told me yeſterday; Muſt ſo many efforts be uſed to force from us that <hi>French</hi> heart that God and Birth has given us? What have we done to merit ſo many misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, and ſuch ſevere puniſhments? We are hunted, we are drove up and down as if we were the Plagues of the Republick; We are treated as the enemies of the Chriſtian Name. In places where the <hi>Jews</hi> are tolerated, they have all manner of liberty, they exerciſe Arts and Merchandize; they are Phyſicians, they are conſulted, the health and life of Chriſtians is put into their hands: And as for us, as if we were infected, we are forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to approach Children that come into the World, we are baniſhed from
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:66400:52"/>the Bars and Faculties, we are remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the King's Perſon, we are baniſhed from Societies, our Charges are taken from us, we are forbidden the uſe of all means that might ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure us from being famiſhed; we are abandoned to the hatred of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, we are deprived of that precious liberty that we had purchaſed by ſo many Services; our Children are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from us, who are a part of our ſelves; we are made to lead a languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life, in lowneſs, in poverty, and often in dark Priſons. Formerly, when Declarations were made againſt us, they were at moſt contented with Regiſtring them in the Rolls. They are at preſent fixed up, they are cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about the Streets as if they were <hi>Gazettes,</hi> to inſpire the People with a ſpirit of fury againſt us. And they have been ſo ſucceſsful, that in the great Cities of <hi>France</hi> we expect to have our Throats cut, one time or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, by a popular Sedition; ſo that we are very near the Inquiſition. Can it be ſaid, that there is Liberty of Conſcience in a Kingdom, where the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:66400:53"/>People are baniſhed, loſe their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and their Goods are confiſcated for Religion's ſake? There needs no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than Fire; and that terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Tribunal of the Inquiſition, which <hi>France</hi> has been hitherto ſo much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of, will be eſtabliſhed there. Are we <hi>Turks,</hi> are we <hi>Infidels?</hi> We believe in Jeſus Chriſt, we believe him the eternal Son of God, we invoke him ſolely; and we have no Idols. We have a ſoveraign reſpect for the Sacred Scriptures, we believe there is a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and a Hell, the Maxims of our Morality are of ſo great a purity, that they dare not contradict them. We have a reſpect for Kings, we are good Subjects, good Citizens, faithful in Commerce: Let us be tryed accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Law, and it will appear if we have been engaged in any Conſpiracy againſt the State, and if we have any ways failed in our duty. Thanks be to God, nothing can ſtagger our fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and the ſtock of love we have for our Prince is not to be drain'd: if it depended on our Enemies, we ſhould be Enemies of the State we
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:66400:53"/>make a part of; they deſign to puſh us on to Crimes, that the King may have a juſt occaſion of ruining us; but they have hitherto miſſed their aim, and are like to do ſo ſtill; the King may ſee it, whilſt that they ſo ſucceſsfully turn the effects of his goodneſs from us, there is not one of us but who is ready to loſe his life for his ſake; we are <hi>Frenchmen</hi> as well as we are Reformed Chriſtians; we would ſhed to the very laſt drop of the blood of our veins to ſerve our King, and for the preſerving our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, even to Death.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>If your <hi>Hugonot</hi> Gentleman has ſtudied Rhetorick, he has not wholly loſt his time.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I know not if he has ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died much, but I eaſily perceive that paſſion is the ſource of his Eloquence; for he told me what I have newly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to you, with a zeal and paſſion that would have moved you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>But could not you have ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped that Orators Mouth with one word, in telling him, that if the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Catholicks in <hi>Holland</hi>
                     <pb n="104" facs="tcp:66400:54"/>and <hi>England</hi> was deſcribed, and in all the Places where the <hi>Hugonots</hi> are Maſters, one might make a repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of their miſeries, much more touching than that they make of the ill Treatment the Religionaries re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in <hi>France?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I did not fail to lay that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Eyes; but he had a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred things to tell me thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>You would oblige me by relating ſome of them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I will tell you them. Firſt, in regard of <hi>Holland,</hi> He told me that I ſuppoſed a thing very far from truth; that the Catholicks are there in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion. I know, ſaid he to me, that you have been in that Country, and you cannot deny, but that they go there with as much liberty to Maſs, as at <hi>Paris.</hi> Would to God, added he, that our Reformed had the ſame Conveniences; there is not a City where the Catholicks are in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable number, but that they have ten or twenty Houſes, wherein Maſs is openly ſaid, and with an intire
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:66400:54"/>liberty. They are ſeen to go in there, they are ſeen to come out from them; and no body dares ſay to them a word againſt it. All that they are troubled at, is that they are not Maſters of the Churches, and that they are obliged to do their Service in particular Houſes. There is in <hi>Holland,</hi> a Country of ſmall extent, ten times more Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticks than there are Miniſters in all <hi>France,</hi> which is very large. There is a compleat Clergy and Hierarchy. <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and all the other great Cities have their Biſhops. Theſe Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops have their Chapter and their Prieſts: There are even Religious Houſes. It is true, that all theſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are ſomething diſguiſed; but are they the leſs known? Would it be diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to unkennel them? They are as well known as the Eccleſiaſticks are in <hi>France,</hi> and are not in the leaſt inſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. It is likewiſe true, that at the ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citation of ſome of the moſt zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of the people, the States former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly iſſued out Placates from time to time, which forbad the exerciſe of the Catholick Religion; but this is no
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:66400:55"/>longer ſo, and it never cauſed one Stone to be took up againſt them. It coſt them about twenty or thirty Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtols for the Sheriff, who put thoſe Placates into his Pocket, and no more talk was heard of them. He added to this, That it is unheard of, that in that Country the Catholicks have been fatigued for the being Convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; they are not at all diſturbed in their Commerce. They are Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, Phyſicians, Artizans, Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates; and, except the Charges of the Government of the State, they are received without diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into all Profeſſions, without ſo much as enquiring of what Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion they are. No Body has Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons brought againſt them upon the account of Relapſes, or for having changed Religion. In a word, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conſcience is entire there, as well as in all other places where the Reformed Religion Rules. I avow to you that I had nothing to reply to this Article; for I had ſeen with my Eyes all that he ſaid. There was one
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:66400:55"/>day with me in a long-Boat, or Schupe, a Prieſt dreſt in black Cloaths, who was not otherwiſe diſguiſed, than that his Coat was ſhort, who ſaid his Breviary before a hundred perſons, with as much liberty as he could have done in <hi>France.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>And what ſaid he of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>He ſaid, that at <hi>London</hi> there are five and twenty Houſes, without counting thoſe of the Ambaſſadours of Catholick Princes, wherein Maſs is publickly ſaid, without any ſearch be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ever made; that the truth is, the liberty is not ſo great in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; but that all Gentlemen had their Almoners and Prieſts in their Houſes, and that all the Catholicks went thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Maſs. But that this was not what he had principally to oppoſe me with. But I'll allow, ſaid he, that Catholicks have leſs liberty in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and in <hi>England,</hi> than the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med have in <hi>France.</hi> But is there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Juſtice to compare, in this regard, <hi>France</hi> with <hi>England?</hi> Why is not
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:66400:56"/>
                     <hi>England</hi> compared with <hi>Spain, Italy, Hungary,</hi> and all the Territories of <hi>Germany,</hi> ſubject to the Houſe of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria?</hi> They oppoſe us with the Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> againſt the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, and we oppoſe the cruelty of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> againſt our people. Is there any Compariſon! The Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks have not the liberty of exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe in <hi>England;</hi> but they live there, they Traffick there, they exerciſe Arts there, they are known there without danger, they even perform their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice there without other hurt, if they be diſcovered, than that they are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid to return. In <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> thoſe they call <hi>Calviniſts</hi> and <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans</hi> are chaſed away like Lyons and Bears: They go in queſt of them, and if they be diſcovered they are burnt alive. If they have the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of making any publick act of their Religion, there are no puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments cruel enough to be inflicted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them. It is ſufficient that they are ſuſpected, or only accuſed of <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raniſme,</hi> for to be caſt into the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the Inquiſition, where they
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:66400:56"/>muſt periſh without Remedy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>That is not ill imagined. For, in fine, it is certain that the Inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion has not yet been eſtabliſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Catholicks, in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries where the Hereſie of <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvin</hi> Govern. But did he ſay nothing to you of more force?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſhall hear; what he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed appeared conſiderable to me, which was, that <hi>Hugonot</hi> Princes can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have the ſame toleration for Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks in their States, that Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Princes can have for <hi>Hugonots;</hi> becauſe that Proteſtant Princes can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be aſſured of the fidelity of their Catholick Subjects, by reaſon they have taken Oaths of fidelity to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prince, whom they conſider as greater than all Kings. It is the Pope; and this Prince is a ſworn Enemy of the Proteſtants. He obliges the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to believe that a Soveraign turned Heretick has forfeited all the Rights of Soveraignty; that they owe him no Obedience; that they may with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punity revolt againſt him, that they may fall upon him as an Enemy of the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:66400:57"/>Chriſtian Name, even to aſſaſſinate him. [See the <hi>Jeſuits Morals, cap.</hi> 3. <hi>Book the Third.</hi>] And thereupon he cited to me, <hi>Mariana, Carolus, Scribanus, Ribadnera, Tolet, Gretſer, Hercun, Amicus, Leſcius, Valentia, Dicatillus,</hi> and ſeveral others, that are cited by the <hi>Janſeniſts,</hi> in the Book of the Jeſuits Morals, and by the Miniſters. All theſe Authors, ſaid he to me, teach conformably to the Divinity of <hi>Rome,</hi> that a Heretick Prince, and Excommunicated by the Pope, is but a particular perſon, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom Armes may be taken; that he may be likewiſe Aſſaſſinated, or poyſoned. He added to this, the examples of ſo many Parricides that have been committed, or attempted according to theſe Maximes. How many times, ſaid he, would they have Aſſaſſinated Queen <hi>Elizabeth?</hi> Prince <hi>Willam</hi> of <hi>Orange</hi> was twice Aſſaſſinated, and loſt his Life the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time. <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, was not he killed by a <hi>Jacobin,</hi> as Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated by the Pope, and ſtript of the Royal Dignity? <hi>John Chaſtel,</hi> did
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:66400:57"/>not he attempt the ſame thing upon <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth: And did not <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villiac</hi> out of a falſe Zeal Aſſaſſinate him. After which he gave me an account of the Gun powder Plot in <hi>England;</hi> by which, in the year 1606. the Catholick had undertaken to blow up the King and all the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees of the Kingdom, by a Mine they had made under the Parliament Houſe. He told me of the Jeſuits <hi>Garnet</hi> and <hi>Oldcorn,</hi> Chief of that Conſpiracy, who were put into the number of the Martyrs, whether they would or no; for the Jeſuit <hi>Garnet</hi> going to Execution, ſome one of his Companions telling him ſoftly in his Ear, that he was going to be a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, he anſwered, <hi>Nunquam audivi parricidam eſſe Martyrem,</hi> I never heard that a <hi>Parricide</hi> was a Martyr. He related to me a hundred ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Stories of that nature. Amongſt others, he told me one that extreamly ſurprized me; he read it to me with all its circumſtances, in a little Book that had been publiſhed by an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, who calls himſelf the King of
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:66400:58"/>
                     <hi>Englands</hi> Chaplain. Thus it is in ſhort: A Divine, who had been the Chaplain of King <hi>Charles</hi> who was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed, turn'd Catholick ſome time before his Maſters Death, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Jeſuits put ſuch confidence in him, that they imparted to him a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry terrible thing; It was a Conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion allowed of by the Pope, about the means of re-eſtabliſhing the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Religion in <hi>England.</hi> The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Catholicks, ſeeing that the King was a Priſoner in the hands of the <hi>Independants,</hi> formed the Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of laying hold on that occaſion to deſtroy the Proteſtant Religion, and re-eſtabliſh the Catholick Religion. They concluded, that the only means of re-eſtabliſhing the Catholick Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and of caſhiering all the Laws that had been made againſt it in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> was to diſpatch the King, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy Monarchy. That they might be authorized and maintained in this great Undertaking, they deputed eighteen Father-Jeſuits to <hi>Rome,</hi> to demand the Popes advice. The mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was agitated in ſecret Aſſemblies,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:66400:58"/>and it was concluded, that it was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted and juſt to put the King to Death. Thoſe Deputies, in their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage through <hi>Paris,</hi> conſulted the <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> who, without waiting for the Opinion of <hi>Rome,</hi> had judged that that enterpriſe was juſt and legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate; and upon the return of the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites, who had taken the Journey to <hi>Rome,</hi> they communicated to the <hi>Sorbonniſts</hi> the Popes Anſwer, of which ſeveral Copies were taken. The Deputies, who had been at <hi>Rome,</hi> being returned to <hi>London,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed the Catholicks in their Deſign. To compaſs this point, they thruſt themſelves in amongſt the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, by diſſembling their Religion. They perſuaded thoſe people that the King muſt be put to Death; and it coſt that poor Prince his Life ſome Months after. But that Death of King <hi>Charles</hi> not having had all the Conſequences that had been hoped; and all <hi>Europe</hi> having cryed out with horrour againſt the Parricide commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Perſon of that poor Prince; they would have drawn in again all
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:66400:59"/>the Copies that had been made of the Conſultation of the <hi>Pope,</hi> and of that of <hi>Sorbonne;</hi> but this <hi>Engliſh</hi> Chaplain who had turned Catholick would not reſtore his; and he has communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it, ſince the return of the Family of the <hi>Stuarts</hi> to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> to ſeveral perſons who are ſtill alive, and were Eye-witneſſes of what I have now told you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>I never heard this before. But the <hi>Engliſh Calviniſts</hi> not producing any authentick pieces to prove this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation, it may be looked upon as a Calumny.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>My <hi>Hugonot</hi> Gentleman would not anſwer for it, for he is very juſt; However he added, that what rendred it very probable, is, that this Conduct is a ſequal of the Divinity of the zealous Catholicks of <hi>Spain, Italy,</hi> and even of <hi>France:</hi> Moreover there are ſeveral Circumſtances which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the thing apparent. By example, he that lately publiſhed this ſtory, had already once publiſhed it in the year 1662, to anſwer a little Book that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted over the <hi>Engliſh Calviniſts,</hi> in
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:66400:59"/>that they had put to death their King. The Divine, who knew the ſtory that I have related, publiſhed it to prove that the Catholicks were guilty of the Crime which the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> were accuſed of. When this ſtory came to light, there was a great emo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Houſe of the Queen-Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the King of <hi>England,</hi> that Houſe being full of Jeſuits; and even that great Lord, who had lead the Jeſuits to <hi>Rome,</hi> and had made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf chief of that Conſpiracy, was one of the principal Officers of the Houſe. They immediately demanded Juſtice of the King, by the means of the Queen-Mother, for the outrage that he who had publiſhed this ſcandalous ſtory had done them. The Doctor offered to prove his Accuſation, and to produce his Witneſſes, who were ſtill living. The great Lord and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer of the Queens Houſe, and the Jeſuits, ſeeing the reſolution of this Man, durſt not puſh him on; they only obtain'd from the King, by the means of the Queen-Mother, that he ſhould be ſilenced. You muſt avow
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:66400:60"/>that there are but few that are inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, who would have been ſo eaſie in ſo terrible an Accuſation. Beſides, it is certain that this Conſultation of <hi>Rome</hi> has been ſeen by ſeveral perſons. If it is falſe, it muſt have been forged by this Chaplain who was turned Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick, and who ſhewed it ſince; now it muſt be confeſſed that this is not very likely. However, as all this is reduced to a ſingle Witneſs, my Gentleman acknowledged that the proof was not wholly in the forms; but he ſtood much upon the late Conſpiracy of <hi>England,</hi> which was diſcovered two years ago, by which half the Kingdom was to have had their Throats cut for the becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Maſters of the reſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>You had a fine opportunity to ſtop him there; for you know ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well that our Catholicks maintain, that it is a perfect Calumny invented by the <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> for the having an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to perſecute the Catholicks. The Jeſuits of St. <hi>Omer,</hi> have they not made appear that their Witneſſes, <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Bedlow,</hi> are falſe Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes?</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:66400:60"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I did not fail to make him that reply; but I avow to you, that my Conſcience did not permit me to rely much upon that Anſwer; for to tell you the truth, I am very much perſwaded that it is falſe: I know that the miſtaken zeal and fury that the falſe Religion inſpires, are capable of a great many things. I eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that it might come into the head of forty of fifty falſe Zealots to lay a train for the ruine of the Party they would deſtroy; but I ſhall never per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my ſelf, that a whole Kingdom ſhould enter into ſuch a Conſpiracy; and that a Parliament, compoſed of five or ſix hundred perſons aſſembled from all the parts of a great State, can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter unanimouſly into the Infernal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of ſuppoſing ſuch a Crime againſt Millions of Innocents, for the having a pretext to perſecute them. And my old <hi>Hugonot,</hi> who is full of fire, and has a great deal of good ſenſe, took me up immediately with much vigour, ſaying, Is it poſſible that ſuch a man as you can ſay ſuch a thing? Ah! leave ſuch ſtories to the Jeſuits
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:66400:61"/>of St. <hi>Omers;</hi> they are accuſed, it is not ſtrange that they defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and the action is ſo black and ſo deteſtable, that they cannot do leſs than diſavow it: If it had had a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſucceſs, they would have been proud of it; at preſent, now they are diſcovered, they deny it. If there needs no more than denying to be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, never any one would be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. They juſtifie themſelves after a pretty manner, they ſend about Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificates and Atteſtations to prove the Contradictions they impute to <hi>Oates:</hi> which are things very hard to make and obtain. In a ſevere Morality, as is that of the Jeſuits, it is a great point for the perſons who are inſtructed in their Schools to give falſe Certificates for the ſaving the Honour of all the Society of the Jeſuits, and even of all the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. Though we had not the Tryals of <hi>Hill, Green, Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Coleman, Ireland, Grove,</hi> and <hi>Pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kering,</hi> which juſtifie the truth of that Conſpiracy; is it credible, that there can be ſuch wicked Judges, as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn to death ſo many innocent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons?
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:66400:61"/>If they had only had a deſign of diſpatching thoſe ſeven perſons, they had clandeſtine way to compaſs it: But they muſt have renounced good Senſe, as well as Conſcience, to try o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly, and in the face of all <hi>Europe,</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple whoſe innocence appearing to the eyes of all the Earth, would have co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with ſhame and infamy thoſe who ſhould have condemned them. If it be only a pretended quarrel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Catholicks, for the having a pretext to ruine them, why are they not ruined? All that has been ſpread abroad on this ſide the Sea are Fables: It has not coſt the life of one perſon, beſides theſe Wretches. The <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks have been for ſome time obliged to remove from <hi>London,</hi> a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great puniſhment indeed for ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable a Conſpiracy! I am certain, that if ſuch a Conſpiracy of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants has been diſcovered in <hi>France</hi> againſt the Catholicks, which God forbid, there would not be at this time one only <hi>Hugonot</hi> in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and the People could not have been hindred from Maſſacring thoſe
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:66400:62"/>who ſhould have eſcaped from the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gours of the Juſtice. The Murder committed in the perſon of Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mondbury Godfrey,</hi> the firſt Juſtice who took the Depoſitions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars of the Conſpiracy, is ſo ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſtrong a proof, that it alone is capable of confounding thoſe who would charge the Proteſtants with the horrible Crime of having invented all that Tragedy, for the aſperſing the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. What had that poor Juſtice done to merit the being aſſaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinated? Is it not clear, that thoſe Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen who ſo well know how to make uſe of the Ponyard and the Knife, had a mind to terrifie all the Judges, and hinder them from pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing an Inqueſt which ſhould coſt the Lives of all thoſe who ſhould make Information and paſs Sentence? <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Bedlow</hi> are falſe Witneſſes! They are then falſe Witneſſes of an admirable Character, falſe Witneſſes who agree perfectly well amongſt themſelves, and never contradict one another: But for all this, they are falſe Witneſſes who have concerted
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:66400:62"/>their buſineſs very ill! If it is a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy, it is a trick invented for the diſhonouring the Society of the Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its, to hang and quarter their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions: Methinks theſe falſe Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes ought to underſtand themſelves ſomething better. On the Seven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of <hi>December</hi> five that were Accuſed were brought to be Examin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and have their Tryal, <hi>Whitebread</hi> the Provincial of the Jeſuits, <hi>William Ireland, John Fenwick, Thomas Picker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and <hi>John Grove: Oates</hi> and <hi>Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi> were produced againſt them as Witneſſes: Theſe two Witneſſes were found to know enough, and to have ſaid enough to cauſe three of thoſe perſons to be condemned, <hi>Ireland, Pickering,</hi> and <hi>Grove: Oates</hi> equally charged the five, but <hi>Bedlow</hi> knew not enough to cauſe <hi>Whitebread</hi> and <hi>Fenwick</hi> to be condemned; inſomuch that they were obliged to ſend back to Priſon theſe two laſt, both of them Jeſuits, and to put off their Tryal till farther Information. This is ſtrange, theſe two falſe Witneſſes are great Fools; <hi>Whitebread</hi> is the chief
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:66400:63"/>of the Conſpiracy, the Provincial of the Jeſuits, he whom they had the moſt reaſon to ruine, and they are ſo imprudent as not to be of intelligence to tell one another what is capable of cauſing him to be condemned, this is not to be comprehended. <hi>Oates</hi> is a falſe Witneſs, he ſays too much to be believed, as is reported. It muſt be confeſſed, that if the Depoſitions of that Man are falſe, it is the ſtrangeſt and moſt unheard of thing in the World. All the examples of fury of paſt Ages wrapt together, do not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach that which is obſerved in this falſe Witneſs. Never was there a link of ſuch terrible Crimes as that Man charges the Accuſed with. <hi>They have,</hi> ſays he, <hi>burnt</hi> London <hi>ſeveral times, they would aſſaſſinate the King, the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the Grandees, and almoſt two thirds of the Inhabitants of the Kingdom, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn the State, deſtroy the Religion, change the Government, and to that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſet whole Rivers of blood a flowing.</hi> Is it credible, that there is ſo wicked a Man in the World, as to charge thoſe that are innocent with ſo many
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:66400:63"/>Crimes? Perhaps that a paſſion of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge might move a Man to lay ſo In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernal a train, to ſatisfie himſelf for ſome outrage he had received. But what outrage does there appear, that <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Bedlow</hi> had received from the <hi>Roman-Catholicks?</hi> The moſt part of thoſe that are accuſed maintain that <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Bedlow</hi> are unkown to them. If they are unknown to them, they have not then done them any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage which might more them to ſo prodigious a revenge: Moreover, by the Teſtimony of thoſe amongſt the accuſed, who confeſs they know their Accuſers, it is certain that both of theſe Witneſſes were <hi>Roman-Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks;</hi> They had not changed their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, had it not been for the horrour of the Plot; they had not become A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtates, had not they been pricked in their Conſciences; they had not any other reaſon to be puſhed on by a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of hatred againſt the <hi>Catholick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> and againſt thoſe who profeſs it: wherefore it was only the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of the Fact which ſtruck them, and obliged them to prevent ſo hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:66400:64"/>effuſion of blood. Methinks that falſe Witneſſes ſhould not charge themſelves with ſo great a number of Facts, leſt they ſhould be expoſed to contradict one another: There need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no more to be ſaid than, in two or three Articles, that ſuch People have Conſpired againſt the State, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Religion, and might have been executed after that manner. But it appears that <hi>Oates</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore heads of accuſation, and makes a Hiſtory of more than fifteen years, well purſued, and well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>. It is requiſite to have an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                        <desc>•••…</desc>
                     </gap>tion that has hardly the like, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                        <desc>•••…</desc>
                     </gap>vent ſuch a Romance ſo well pur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4+ letters">
                        <desc>••••…</desc>
                     </gap>. I likewiſe find, that thoſe Witne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s are very bold to invent ſuch horrible De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions againſt People who ſo well know how to make uſe of the Knife for the diſpatching their Enemies, as appears by the Death of <hi>Godfrey.</hi> The good Nature of thoſe good Fathers would be very great, if they did not revenge themſelves on <hi>Oats</hi> and <hi>Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,</hi> in caſe that their Depoſitions were true; but it is hardly credible,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:66400:64"/>that it would reach ſo far as to let two Impoſtors live peaceably, who had charged them with the moſt horrid Calumnies that Hell had ever imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. And if they have a deſign to deſtroy them, it is hard if they do not ſucceed in it ſooner or later: The King's Safe-guards, and the Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Parliament, will little help them. Wherefore if <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi> were falſe Witneſſes, they are great Fools to expoſe themſelves into ſo great a danger in this life for the damning themſelves alſo in the other. In fine, my <hi>Hugonot</hi> Gentleman told me, What have we to do with <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Bedlow</hi> to prove the Truth of that Conſpiracy? Let us take them, if you will, from off the Scene, and judge of the buſineſs by <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Letters to Father <hi>le Cheiſe,</hi> and to ſome others. Theſe Letters have been acknowledged, the accuſed have not denied them. There is one to the Pope's Nuncio at <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> Dated the 9th of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1674. which ſays in proper terms, <hi>That their deſign advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced apace, and that they ſhould quickly
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:66400:65"/>ſee the ruine of the Proteſtant Party.</hi> Is any thing of more force than what <hi>Coleman</hi> ſays to Father <hi>le Cheiſe,</hi> in one of the Letters he wrote to him; <hi>We have undertaken a great Work; it is no leſs than the Converſion of three Kingdoms, and the entire ſubverſion of that peſtilent Hereſie which has for ſo long a time rul'd over this Northern part of the World: And we have never had ſo great hopes ſince the Reign of Our Queen</hi> Mary. And towards the end of the Letter, he powerfully ſollicites Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>le Cheiſe</hi> to obtain ſuccours of Money and Arms for putting in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution this great Deſign. It is perhaps by the way of Preaching that <hi>Coleman</hi> pretended to Convert thoſe three Kingdoms! Arms and Money are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neceſſary to give efficacy to Grace and Preaching! It is certainly, in that ſpirit of Zeal and well regulated De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, that <hi>Coleman</hi> ſays; <hi>Though I had a Sea of Blood, and a thouſand Lives, I would willingly loſe them all for the execution of this Deſign; and if to bring it to paſs, it was requiſite, to deſtroy an hundred Heretick Kings, I
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:66400:65"/>would do it.</hi> Theſe words are pretty ſtrong: It is <hi>Bedlow</hi> who has report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, and ſays, he heard them. If he invented them in cold Blood, and without being moved with Anger, I find him admirable in the art of feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Paſſions: For it muſt be avowed, that theſe expreſſions give us a lively image of a Man the moſt moved and the moſt concerned that has ever been ſeen. For a Man of War, as <hi>Bedlow.</hi> I find he would be very Eloquent, and that he would ſucceed admirably well in compoſing the Character of a Stage-Hero. Let us ſpeak ſeriouſly, one muſt have renounced all Modeſty to dare to maintain that all this great action is only a Comedy and a Ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>But as concerning Father <hi>le Cheiſe,</hi> whom your <hi>Hugonot</hi> ſpoke of in the affair of <hi>Coleman,</hi> I have admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red how the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have aſperſed him by the publication of <hi>Colemans</hi> Tryal. For this Father is every where there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, in the middle, beginning, and the end; and it is upon him that the moſt convincing proofs turn that are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:66400:66"/>againſt <hi>Coleman.</hi> It appears that this F. <hi>Jeſuit</hi> was of the Party, and that he was engaged very deep into the deſign of re-eſtabliſhing the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Religion in <hi>England,</hi> by fire and by the effuſion of Blood.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>My Gentleman made me that remark, and told me thereupon, Methinks that the King's Equity ought to move him not to hearken to ſuch a Man in what regards the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts of the Subjects of the Reformed Religion. What may not the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants of <hi>France</hi> fear from a Man who has been ſo deeply engaged in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of cutting the Throats of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny millions of Proteſtants? What Counſels may not he give to the King againſt us, who would have ſet whole Rivers of the Blood of our Brethren a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlowing, and make a St. <hi>Bartholomew</hi> beyond the Seas? Though he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent of the Affair of <hi>England,</hi> the advices he gives againſt us ought to be ſuſpected. For it is clear, that he ought to have a great reſentment of the fierce accuſations that have been formed againſt him, and that he
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:66400:66"/>would have the intention to revenge himſelf on the Proteſtants of <hi>France,</hi> for the outrages that he might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to have receiv'd from the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants of <hi>England.</hi> Wherefore it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that the King ought to conſider him as our declared enemy, and as a paſſionate enemy, and not as a zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Catholick. However, this Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Jeſuit</hi> brags he is the Maſter of all the King's Reſolutions in what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns us. It is he, if he may be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, to whom the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> is indebted for all the ſevere Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that have been made againſt us. And when the Declaration was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, which forbids Catholicks to turn to the Reformed Religion, he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the Aſſembly of the Clergy with that Declaration in his hand, with a triumphing air, and ſaid, <hi>Here is the piece that has been ſo long a ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciting; it is I that have obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it.</hi> If this man be ſo powerful o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the King's mind, as he brags he is, the Proteſtants of <hi>France</hi> could not be ſecure of their lives. We know from good hands, added he, that the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:66400:67"/>Members of the Council are not too well ſatisfied in, that the affairs His Majeſty was uſed to conſult them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, and believe them in, are at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent put into the hands of a <hi>Jeſuit.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>For my part, I avow to you, I am not too well perſwaded no more than you, that this Conſpiracy of the <hi>Engliſh Catholicks</hi> is a fiction: But I endeavour to perſwade it to others, becauſe that I wiſh it were ſo for the honour of the Catholick Religion, which never ought to inſpire ſuch Deſigns.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>Be it as it will, my <hi>Hugonot</hi> Gentleman concluded from all this, that a Proteſtant Prince can never be aſſured of the Fidelity of his Catholick Subjects. On the contrary, ſaid he, the Proteſtants are ſubject to their Prince out of Conſcience, and out of a Principle of their Religion: They acknowledge no other Superiour than their King. and do not believe that for the cauſe of Hereſie it is permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, either to kill a legitimate Prince, or to refuſe him obedience.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:66400:67"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>You might have asked him, if what the <hi>Engliſh</hi> do at preſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> agrees well with that Divinity? Becauſe that he is ſaid to be Catholick, they would declare him uncapable of ſucceeding his Brother.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I had not time to propoſe to him that difficulty, for he prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it. It is true, ſaid he to me, that the troubles which are in <hi>England</hi> ſeem to tend towards the refuſing O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is a Catholick. When a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign is mounted upon the Throne by legitimate means, it ſeems, ſaid I to him, that he ought at leaſt to have as much priviledge as his Subjects, and enjoy as well as them the Liberty of Conſcience. That is true, anſwered he me, when he has not bound his hands by his own Laws. But by the Laws of the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> which are the Laws of the King as well as of the State, the King is obliged not to ſuffer any other Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in the State, than the Proteſtant Religion. Theſe Laws cannot be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:66400:68"/>but by the Parliament jointly with the King; becauſe that in that Kingdom, for the making or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing Laws, the King can do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing without the Parliament, nor the Parliament without the King. Wherefore if the Parliament is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Repealing of theſe Laws, if they muſt ſubſiſt, and while that they ſubſiſt, the King has not power to eſtabliſh in his Family a different Religion from that of the State. You know, ſaid he to me, that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>England</hi> have great Priviledges, and that the Kings have not the Right to do all that they pleaſe. Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, added he, when there is a Prince to be eſtabliſhed, the States of the Kingdom, who are obliged to be careful of the Preſervation of the Religion, are authorized to take all their Sureties, that no change may be made therein: Thus they muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther remove from the Throne, if they have the Right to do ſo, he who would mount into it to ruin the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; or at leaſt, they ought to bridle his Authority for the hindring
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:66400:68"/>him from making changes. The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of <hi>Henry</hi> the 4th, before he turned Catholick, was an Obſtacle to his eſtabliſhment upon the Throne, which he would never have ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted though he was the legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate Heir of the Crown.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>This man is very knowing. He certainly came prepared upon the matter: For, <hi>extempore,</hi> he could not have given to his reaſons ſo great an air of likelihood.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>He came, without doubt, prepared; and I likewiſe perceived that he daily conſulted people more knowing than himſelf: For he clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and argued ſtrongly the next day, upon ſuch points as I had found him weak in the day before. One of the points of which he ſpoke to me with the moſt zeal and paſſion, was that of good Faith. They oppoſe againſt us, ſaid he to me, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> Catholicks: But what has been promiſed to thoſe people that has not been performed? The United Provinces of the Low Countries are entred into the Union with this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:66400:69"/>of not ſuffering any other Religion in their States, than the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant. Though <hi>England</hi> was refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med under <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards under <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> by ſeveral Acts of Parliament, which are the fundamental Laws of the Kingdom, it was ordered that no other Religion ſhould be ſuffered than that the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glicane</hi> Church made choice of, and that they would not ſuffer the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of thoſe, whom they at preſent call Nonconformiſts. It was even forbidden to the Prieſts and Monks to ſet Foot in <hi>England,</hi> and to make any abode there. However they have not kept up to this rigour, and every one knows that there is at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent above ten thouſand Prieſts and Monks diſguiſed in <hi>England,</hi> and that there has ever been ſo. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore more has been given to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, than was promiſed them. But in <hi>France,</hi> where we live under favourable Edicts, they have promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed us what they have not performed: It is only againſt us that they make profeſſion of not performing what
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:66400:69"/>they have promiſed. The Edicts of Pacification are in all the Formes that perpetual Laws ought to be; they are verified by the Parliaments, they are confirmed by a hundred De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, which followed by Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, and by a thouſand Royal Words: In fine, they have been laid as irrevocable Laws, and as founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Peace of the State. We rely upon the good Faith of ſo many promiſes; and on a ſudden we ſee ſnatcht from us, what we looked upon as our greateſt ſecurity, and which we had poſſeſſed for above a hundred years. Thus there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Title, nor Preſcription, nor E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts, nor Arreſts, nor Declarations which can put us in Safety. This is what he told me, and I avow to you, that this part put me in pain, for I am a Slave of my Word, and an Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>later of good Faith: I look upon it as the only Rampart of Civil Society; and I conceive that States and Publick perſons are no leſs obliged to keep what they promiſe, than particular men.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:66400:70"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>That is true. But do not you know that the health of the people, and the publick good, is the Soveraign Law? Very often we muſt ſuffer, and even do ſome Evil, for the good of the State. Peaces and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are daily broken, which have been ſolemnly ſworn, becauſe that the publick intereſt requires it ſhould be ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>My <hi>Hugonot</hi> made himſelf that difficulty, and told me thereupon, When War is declared againſt Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, to the prejudice of Treaties of Peace and Alliances, this is done in the Forms. They publiſh Manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto's; they expoſe, or at leaſt, they ſuppoſe Grievances and Infractions in the Articles of the Treaty, that have been made by thoſe againſt whom War is declared. When a Soveraign revokes the Graces that he had done his Subjects, it is ever un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretext that they have rendered themſelves unworthy of them. But are we accuſed, or can we be accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of having tampered in any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy, of having had Intelligence
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:66400:70"/>with the Enemies of the State, of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving wanted Love, Fidelity and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience towards our Soveraigns? If it be ſo, let us be brought to Tryal, let the Criminals be informed againſt, and let the Innocent be diſtinguiſhed from thoſe that are Guilty. We ſpeak boldly therein, becauſe we are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain they can reproach us with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; and we know that his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty himſelf has very often given Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of our Fidelity. He knows that we did not enter into any of the Parties that have been made againſt his Service, ſince he has been upon the Throne. During the troubles of his minority, it may be ſaid, that none but thoſe Cities we were Maſters of remained Loyal. When the Gates of <hi>Orleans</hi> were ſhut upon the King, he went to <hi>Gien;</hi> and that City was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be guilty of the ſame Crime, without the vigour of a <hi>Hugonot,</hi> who peirced with his Sword in his hand to the Bridge, and let it down himſelf: This action was known, and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penced; for the King immediately made him Noble who had done it.
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:66400:71"/>VVe had not any part in the diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances of <hi>Bordeaux,</hi> in thoſe of <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany</hi> and <hi>Auvergne,</hi> nor in the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy of the Chevalier <hi>de Rohan:</hi> Not one <hi>Hugonot</hi> was engaged in theſe Criminal Caſes. The King has been pleaſed to acknowledge it; and we look upon the Teſtimony of ſo great a King as a great Recompence. But our Enemies, who continually ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit him to our ruin, ought to be mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, that it would be more civil in them, to leave the King the liberty of following his inclinations: Theſe would without doubt move him, to preſerve the effects of his kindneſs for people who have preſerved for him an inviolable Fidelity. This is what he told me upon that point; and I confeſs I was in great perplexity how to anſwer him; for I durſt not make uſe of that Maxime that I have ſeen often maintain'd by ſome people, that one is not obliged to keep Faith with Hereticks. I have ever admired that ſaying of <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth: He cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Martin Luther</hi> to come to <hi>Worms,</hi> and gave him ſafe Conduct, and his
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:66400:71"/>Imperial word, that no hurt ſhould be done him. But not having been able to obtain from him what he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, he ſent him back; ſome one would have perſuaded <hi>Charles,</hi> That he ought to cauſe <hi>Luther</hi> to be ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, without having regard to the ſafe Conduct, becauſe that this man was of the Character of thoſe to whom one is not obliged to keep ones word. Though good Faith were baniſhed from all the Earth, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered he, it ought to be found in an Emperour. A ſaying very worthy of ſo great a Man! But tell me, Sir, is it not an Opinion very contrary to that of <hi>Charles</hi> the 5th, that is the cauſe that ſo little Conſcience is made of keeping with thoſe people what has been promiſed them?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>This Doctrine that one is not obliged to keep Faith with Hereticks, is taug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> by ſome Caſuiſts, and they pretend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> it is founded upon the Authority of the Council of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> becauſe that that Council cauſed <hi>John Hus</hi> to be burnt, contrary to the Faith of the ſafe Conduct that the
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:66400:72"/>Emperour <hi>Sigismond</hi> had granted him; and <hi>Jerome</hi> of <hi>Prague,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the ſafe Conduct that the ſame Council had given him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>This Morality ever appeared to me terrible; and I have been often ſcandalized at the Conduct of that great Council of <hi>Conſtance.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>The moſt part of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks reject that Morality, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain we are obliged to keep Faith with all the World, without excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Infidels and Hereticks; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe there would never be any Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty between the <hi>Turks</hi> and the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, that were real. It is pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the Council of <hi>Conſtance</hi> has not eſtabliſhed this Maxime, That we are not obliged to keep with Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks what we have promiſed them. <hi>John Hus</hi> had no ſafe Conduct from the Council, he had only the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours; and thereupon the Council in the Nineteenth Seſſion declared, That any ſafe Conduct, granted by the Emperour, by Kings, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Secular Princes to Hereticks-could not do prejudice to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:66400:72"/>Faith, and to the Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, and could not hinder from proceeding in the Tribunal of the Church, to the puniſhment of Hereticks, who had provided them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with ſuch a ſafe Conduct. Thus the Council did not violate its promiſe, for it never gave any; neither did it oblige the Emperour to violate his Faith: But the Eccleſiaſtical Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal, that had not given any word, made <hi>John Hus</hi> his Proceſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>That diſtinction ſeems plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to me: I have heard ſay, that the Church does not put its hand into blood: When <hi>John Hus</hi> was convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of Hereſie by the Council, he was delivered without doubt to the ſecular Arm to be burnt. Thoſe Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Judges, were not they Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Judges? Thus the Emperour vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated his ſafe Conduct, in permitting his Judges to put a Man to Death, to whom he had promiſed all ſecurity. But what do they ſay of <hi>Jerome</hi> of <hi>Prague,</hi> to whom the Council it ſelf had given a ſafe Conduct, and yet was burnt?</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:66400:73"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>They ſay that the Council, in the ſafe Conduct that was given to <hi>Jerome</hi> of <hi>Prague,</hi> had inſerted this Clauſe, <hi>Salva Juſtitia;</hi> that thus they had only promis'd to warrant <hi>Jerome</hi> of <hi>Prague</hi> from violence, and not from the arreſts of Juſtice: But I avow to you that all this is not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of juſtifying the Conduct of that Council. Neither does it paſs in <hi>France</hi> for a Rule that they will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. If they do not keep with the <hi>Hugonots</hi> all that has been promiſed them, it is not that they ground themſelves upon the Morality and the Conduct of the Council of <hi>Conſtance.</hi> They do not pretend to depart from good Faith; they make profeſſion of keeping the Edict of <hi>Nantes:</hi> Do you not ſee this at the Head of all the Declarations which are made againſt them? And now lately, in that by which the Catholicks are forbidden to embrace the <hi>P. R.</hi> Religion, upon pain of Confiſcation of goods, loſs of Honour, and Baniſhment; though that never any Declaration was made that was more contrary to the Edicts
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:66400:73"/>of <hi>Nantes.</hi> We have one called <hi>Bernard,</hi> and another Lawyer of the City of <hi>Poictiers,</hi> called <hi>Tilleau,</hi> who have made large Commentaries upon the Edict of <hi>Nantes,</hi> for to make ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that without formally revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that Edict, the <hi>Hugonots</hi> may be deprived of all that Edict grants them, in giving to every one of the Articles Interpretations and Gloſſes that would never have been im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                        <desc>•••…</desc>
                     </gap>ed: And theſe are the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>This is good for an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap>ing But after all, this does not ſatisfie the Conſcience, and one is no leſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of having violated his word: For thoſe who obtain Arreſts againſt the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> according to the Gloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of <hi>Bernard</hi> and <hi>Tilleau,</hi> are well perſwaded that they are Gloſſes of <hi>Orleans,</hi> which overturn the Text. But do you know what I told my <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonot,</hi> to ſtop his Mouth, upon theſe Infractions in the Edicts?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>Perhaps you told him, that one is not obliged to keep a word that has been extorted by violence; that
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:66400:74"/>the <hi>Hugonots</hi> have obtained thoſe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts by main force: That ours were conſtrained to yield to the miſery of the times; but that at preſent the King is in Right of Nulling thoſe promiſes. Our Advocates plead daily thus at the Bars, and there are likewiſe grave Authors who write it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>You have gueſſed right: but thereupon my <hi>Hugonot</hi> grew ſtrangely paſſionate. Ah! this is, ſaid he, a cruelty we cannot ſuffer. This is our ſtrength, and they are ſo bold as to attacque us in this part, as if it was our weak ſide. It is true, that we were armed ſome years before that the Edict of <hi>Nantes</hi> was made. But in favour of whom did we bear thoſe Arms? It was to eſtabliſh the Illuſtrious branch of <hi>Bourbon</hi> upon the Throne, that belonged to it. VVe ſhall ever be proud of having ſhed the pureſt of our Blood, to reſtore to <hi>France</hi> it's legitimate Kings there was a deſign of depriving it of. After this growing more cool, he made me an abridgement of the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:66400:74"/>of the League. He made me ſee that the Houſe of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> in that time, aimed leſs at Hereſy than at the Crown. He made me remember that from the time of <hi>Charles</hi> the 9th, the Princes of that Houſe cauſed a Book to be Printed, for the proving their Genealogy, and to make appear that they were deſcended in a direct Line from the Second Race of our Kings, for the making way to the Crown. He acquainted me that there was at the ſame time a Concordat paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed between the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Montmorency,</hi> and the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall <hi>de St. Andrew,</hi> which was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Triumvirate. One of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of that Concordat boar, in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs terms, that the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> ſhould have in charge to deface intirely the name of the Family and Race of the <hi>Bourbons. Henry</hi> the Third, ſaid he to me, could he be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected of Hereſie, or aider of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks? Never was any man more linked to the Catholick Church than he. Yet the Houſe of <hi>Guiſe</hi> had ſworn his ruin: They would have
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:66400:75"/>ſhaved him, which they highly threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him with, and they one day writ upon the Chappel of the <hi>Battes,</hi> to the <hi>Auguſtins</hi> of <hi>Paris,</hi> theſe four <hi>French</hi> Verſes.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>The Bones of thoſe who here lye dead,</l>
                     <l>Like a <hi>Burgundy</hi> Croſs to thee are ſhown,</l>
                     <l>Do make appear thy days are fled;</l>
                     <l>And that thou ſhalt loſe thy Crown.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>They are of the ſame ſenſe with thoſe two Latin Verſes which were found ſet upon the Palace Dyal.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Qui dedit ante duas, unam abſtulit, altera nutas;</l>
                     <l>Tertia tonſoris nunc facienda manu.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>The Faction of the Houſe of <hi>Guiſe</hi> cauſed this to be done: And this poor Prince, after a thouſand delays and troubles, reſolved at length to make that execution ſo famous in our Hiſtory; it is that of the Duke and Cardinal of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> who were execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:66400:75"/>at the States of <hi>Blois.</hi> That Prince muſt needs have ſeen his ruin approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and inevitable to come to that, ſince that he well foreſaw that this blow would raiſe him ſo many ſtorms, and give him ſo much trouble. Who knows not that the Faction of <hi>Rome,</hi> and of <hi>Spain,</hi> had a Deſign of raſing the Houſe of <hi>Lorrain</hi> upon the Throne of <hi>France,</hi> for the excluding the Houſe of <hi>Bourbon?</hi> In the year 1587. the Pope ſent to the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> a Sword engraven with flames, telling him by the Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all the Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> it only belonged to <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Lorrain</hi> to bear the arms of the Church, and to be the Chief thereof. Almoſt all the Kingdom was engaged in that Spirit of revolt: The King found no other ſupport, than the King of <hi>Navar</hi> and of his <hi>Hugonots.</hi> It was <hi>Chaſtillon,</hi> the Son of the Admiral <hi>de Coligny,</hi> who ſaved the King from the hands of the Duke of <hi>Mayenne</hi> at <hi>Tours.</hi> This Chief of the League cryed to him, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire you white Scarfs; retire you <hi>Chaſtillon,</hi> it is not you we aim at, it
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:66400:76"/>is the Murderer of your Father. And in truth, <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, then Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> was Preſident in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil when the Reſolution was taken of making the Maſſacre of St. <hi>Bartholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mew,</hi> in which the Admiral <hi>Coligny</hi> periſhed. But his Son, forgetting that injury, to ſave his King, anſwered thoſe Rebels; You are Traytors to your Country; and when the Service of the Prince and State is concerned, I know how to lay under my feet all revenge and particular intereſt; he added, that after the Aſſaſſinate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by the League, in the perſon of <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth was ready to ſee himſelf abandoned by his moſt faithful Servants, becauſe of the Proteſtant Religion, which he made profeſſion of; which appears by a Declaration that this Prince made in the form of an Harangue to the Lords of his Army, on the 8th day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1589, in which he ſays, that he had been informed that his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Nobility ſet a report on foot that they could not ſerve him, unleſs he made profeſſion of the <hi>Roman</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:66400:76"/>and that they were going to quit his Army. Nothing but the firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and fidelity of the <hi>Hugonots</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held this wavering Party. He muſt be, ſaid my Gentleman, the falſeſt of men, who diſſembles the Ardour and Zeal with which thoſe of our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on maintained that juſt Cauſe of the Houſe of <hi>Bourbon,</hi> againſt the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of the League: And to prove, ſaid he, that their intereſt was not the only cauſe of their fidelity, we muſt ſee what they did when <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth turned <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick. It cannot be ſaid but that they then ſtrove to have a King of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: However, there was not one who bated any thing of his Zeal and Fidelity, the King was peaceable poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſour of the Crown, the League was beaten down, he was Maſter in <hi>Paris,</hi> he was reconciled to the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> when the Edict of <hi>Nantes</hi> was granted and publiſhed: Our <hi>Hugo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nots</hi> were no longer armed, nor in a condition of obtaining any thing by force of arms, ſince that the Change of Religion had reduced all the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:66400:77"/>Catholicks</hi> to him, he would have been in a State of reſiſting their vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. It was the ſole acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the King, and of good <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> that obliged all <hi>France</hi> to give Peace to a Party that had ſhed their Blood with ſo much Zeal and Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the conſerving the Crown, and the reſtoring it to its legitimate Heirs. I avow that we did our Duty; but are not thoſe to be thanked who do what they ought? How is it poſſible that theſe things are at preſent worn out of the memory of men? I am certain, that if the King was made to read the Hiſtory of his Grand-father, he would preſerve ſome inclination for the Children of thoſe who ſacrific'd themſelves to the glory of his Houſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>It cannot be denied that this Party has rendered great Services to <hi>Henry</hi> IV, and to the Crown. But the Queſtion is, to know whether much be owing them upon that Account. Have not they been well paid, by a repoſe of ſo many years, which they have enjoyed ſince that time?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſaid to my old Gentleman,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:66400:77"/>after all, in the bottom you have no reaſon to complain: All that is done, is with deſign of Converting and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving you; You ought to conſider that it is the Intereſt of a State to have but one Religion: Every one knows, that the diverſity of Religions is the ſource of Diviſions, and that often it cauſes great troubles. You need on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly read the Hiſtory of the laſt Age to be aſſured of it. He thereupon anſwered me, You open me a great field, permit me that I ſtop a little here, and that I make you ſee, firſt, That that is a miſunderſtood Zeal which endeavours at preſent the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the Proteſtants of <hi>France:</hi> in the ſecond place, That this Deſign can never have the ſucceſs that is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected: and in fine, that nothing is more oppoſite to the true Intereſts of the King, than the Conduct they at preſent hold with us. When I had promiſed him Audience, he ſpoke to me much to this purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, As for the Zeal which moves, at preſent, ſo many People to make what they call Converſions, I muſt
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:66400:78"/>tell you, that I never conceived that real Converſions were to be procured by ſuch means: They would ſave us you ſay, in good time, but let us be ſaved by honeſt means: They damn us by endeavouring to ſave us, even though the Religion to which they would bring us were good: They make us ſell our Religion, they make a traffick of Souls, threatnings and promiſes are employed; no employ is given, no grace granted, without adding to it for Condition the Change of Religion: The ſimple are ſurpriz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Children are taken away, they lay hold on the irreligion of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain people, either Libertines or Brutes, who having no ſenſe of God, are ever ready to betray their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences for Money; In effect ſuch people are paid, the King is put to great Charges to recompence the Converts, that is to ſay, for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining perſons who have neither Religion nor Piety. It is certain, that of a thouſand which turn Catholicks, there is perhaps not one who does it out of a motive of Conſcience: The
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:66400:78"/>one has loſt his ſuite at Law, and his Goods, and knows not where to put his head; another ready to loſe an Employ which kept him alive, and which they would have taken from him, ſacrifices his Conſcience for the preſervation of his Fortune. A Child angry with its Parents, who had puniſhed it, revenges it ſelf on them, by becoming of another Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion than theirs. A young Woman, who has loſt her honour, goes to ſeek it in the ſtrongeſt Party, and is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to cover all her infamy with the vail of Converſion. If the Grandees be excepted, who are tempted by plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and invited by hopes of ſome conſiderable advancement; theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts are almoſt all ſuch perſons as are the dreggs of the people, who are drawn in by motives worthy of the baſeneſs of their Birth and their Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage: Let the holy Writ be read, and ſee if the Apoſtles and their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours ever made uſe of ſuch-like means for the Converting <hi>Pagans</hi> and <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels.</hi> And with all the pains that are taken, they will never ſucceed in the
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:66400:79"/>deſign of reducing by theſe kind of ways all the Proteſtants of <hi>France</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. Great Progreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes have been made for ſome late years, but do they believe that that will always laſt? A long Peace had retained in our Party a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the ungodly, who ſtuck to our Religion, becauſe they did not find themſelves better elſewhere. Thoſe people who never had any Religion, make no difficulty now to change it; But our Party will purge it ſell, and when it is drained of the ungodly ones, and when there is none amongſt us but honeſt people who have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevered out of Principle of Conſcience, it will be no longer ſeen that ſo many perſons yield to promiſes and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings; thus the numerous Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons will ceaſe. Moreover, you muſt know, Sir, that they take you to be very credulous, when they tell you of numerous converſions. There are five or ſix Bigots in <hi>France,</hi> who have erected themſelves into Converters, keeping a Regiſter of their Converts, and from time to time ſhew the King
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:66400:79"/>theſe Regiſters; but they fill up theſe Catalogues after a ſtrange manner. Beſides, theſe Gentlemen Converters are plaid upon, and they are even willing to be cheated, that they may afterwards cheat his Majeſty; becauſe they know that he is liberal, even to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rofuſion, to thoſe who turn <hi>Catholiks.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>here are Rogues, who never having <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Proteſtants, not ſo much as by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> on, go and put themſelves up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                        <desc>•••…</desc>
                     </gap> the Catalogue of Converts, that they may be rewarded for their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Converſion. And in fine, where are theſe Converſions made? It is at <hi>Paris,</hi> and in ſome other great Cities of <hi>France,</hi> where there are Miſſions and Houſes of propagation eſtabliſhed, where the people are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually ſollicited by Promiſes and by Threatnings. But in all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, and particularly in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, there are hardly any Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſeen: perhaps within twenty years one might count ten or twelve thouſand perſons, who from <hi>Hugo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nots</hi> have turned Catholicks; what is this to near two Millions of Souls of
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:66400:80"/>that Religion, there are in <hi>France,</hi> and when will they then have done?</p>
                  <p>I know not, continued he, how they can hope to draw in ſo great a number of people; there is nothing more difficult to be forced out of the mind than ſentiments of Religion, and nothing more difficult to be root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of a Country than a Sect that has had time to fortifie it ſelf there, and which is ſetled in its Opinions: Fire and Sword cannot extirpate it. Do we not ſee it proved in the <hi>Spaniſh Low-Countries?</hi> From the time that the exerciſe and profeſſion of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion was forbidden there, ought it not to be extinguiſhed? yet there are ſtill found a great number of thoſe People, whom they call <hi>Guiſes.</hi> And for my part, I cannot forbear believing, That the Doctrine and Opinions of the <hi>Albigenſes</hi> have been preſerved in <hi>Languedock,</hi> as a Fire hid under Cinders, from the time of thoſe <hi>Albigenſes</hi> even to <hi>Calvin</hi>'s time. And it is to this that I attribute, that our Reformation has made greater Progreſſes in that Province, than in
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:66400:80"/>the others. All thoſe who would make ſerious reflections upon what I have now ſaid, will grant, that they will never compaſs the reducing the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of <hi>France</hi> into the <hi>Roman</hi> Church: And thus all the pains that are taken, and all the ills they ſuffer, will only make them miſerable and raiſe Malecontents.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>This is certainly all that your Orator could imagine for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining his two firſt Propoſitions? I am very impatient to know what he could ſay for the maintaining the third, that the deſign of re-uniting the Religions in <hi>France</hi> is againſt the Intereſts of the King and State; for it is a ſtrange Paradox, common ſenſe dictates that there is not a greater good in the World, both for Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals and Spirituals, preferable to that of ſeeing in a State an unanimous conſent in matters of Religion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>When my Gentleman was at the part I left you at, I perceived his forces failed him: You have put me, ſaith he, upon a Chapter that requires ſomething more knowledge
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:66400:81"/>than I have. A Souldier is not obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to know more than the Hiſtory of his Age; but give me leave to bring you to morrow a man who will tell you more therein than I can.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>You was not ſorry at this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of breaking off a Converſation that gave you time to breath.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>You are in the right, I wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly granted him what he deſired; we parted, and the day after at the hour we had appointed, I ſaw him en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, accompanied with an old Civil Lawyer of his Party; who in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quel ſeemed to me a pretty able man. After the firſt Complements, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan with telling me; You are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, Sir, in permitting a man, who found himſelf too weak, to go ſeek for ſuccours. This Gentleman has informed me of the ſubject of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations you had with him. He told me where you ſtopped, and if you think fit, we will renew it in the ſame place.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>Methought he had done with proving, that they would never ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in the deſign of reducing all the
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:66400:81"/>
                     <hi>Hugonots</hi> of <hi>France</hi> into the boſom of the Church.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>I thought ſo as well as you. But this Gown-man did not judge that the Souldier had ſaid enough up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that point; wherefore he continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the matter thus. You muſt grant, Sir, that in the riſe and fall of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and Schiſms, there is ſomething Divine, and which paſſes our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: They are deceived, who imagine that the wounds of the Church are to be cured by Humane means. God for the puniſhing the coldneſs and negligence of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Paſtors, ſuffers the Devil to ſow Weeds in the field of the Church; and when his anger is appeaſed, he cauſes thoſe Schiſms to ceaſe, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhes thoſe Hereſies that his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice had permitted; and he does it by means which he alone is Maſter of. It is true that thouſands of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies which were in the firſt Ages, are no longer in being: <hi>Arrianiſme,</hi> that made ſo much noiſe in the World, is quite gone. But to whom do we owe this? It is neither to violence nor pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments:
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:66400:82"/>Good Emperours never made uſe of them; and the effuſion of blood is contrary to the good Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Church. The <hi>Arrians</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed were perſecutors, but were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver perſecuted. It is not by ſuch-like means as thoſe by which they pretend at preſent to Convert the <hi>Hugonots</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> to wit, by depriving them of their Temples, and removing them from Charges, and doing them injuſtices, and violating the promiſes that were made them, and reducing them to die of Hunger: Humane will does the more ſtrive againſt theſe ſort of Oppoſitions. Neither was it by the way of Councils: For after the Decrees of the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> of that of <hi>Sardica,</hi> and of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral others that have been held againſt the <hi>Arrians,</hi> their Sect has multiplyed and has reigned with more inſolence than before; that Sect is inſenſibly extinguiſhed of it ſelf, and no one knows how, after having exerciſed its furies in <hi>Aſia, Greece,</hi> and <hi>Africa,</hi> during more than two hundred years. But this Hereſie being thus extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:66400:82"/>to conclude from thence, that with the cares that might be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, all other Hereſies might be ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled, and affirm that a Schiſm cannot laſt long; that after having ſubſiſted ſome time it muſt neceſſarily ceaſe, is to be but little acquainted with the Hiſtory of the Church. The Schiſm and Hereſie of <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> have not they ſtill laſted to this day in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> from the year 430, that is to ſay, for above twelve hundred years? The Schiſm of the <hi>Eutychians</hi> is of no la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a date than that of the <hi>Neſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> than about twenty or five and twenty years: for <hi>Eutyches</hi> and <hi>Dioſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> were condemned in the year 451. in the Council of <hi>Chalcedon;</hi> and from that time the followers of thoſe two Men have filled all the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and the <hi>South,</hi> under the names of <hi>Euty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chians, Severians, Auphalans, Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, Jacobites, Cophtes,</hi> and even of <hi>Abyſſyns.</hi> For all theſe People who ſtill at this day make the greateſt part of the <hi>Aſian</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Churches, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to the Schiſm of <hi>Eutyches.</hi> It is above ſeven hundred years that the
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:66400:83"/>Latins are in Schiſm with the <hi>Greeks,</hi> and all the pains that the Popes and Eaſtern Emperours have given them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at ſeveral times, have not been able to extinguiſh this Schiſme. If Prudence, Cares and Vigilance have not been able to bring to paſs the ruine of Sects that were not founded upon Truth, and who had violated Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by their Separation; they ought not to hope to ruin the Party of the Reformed, which is ſupported by Truth, has purged the Church of ſo many errours, and has in no manner violated Charity, in ſeparating it ſelf from a Church, that choſe rather to chaſe away from its boſome, than ſuffer any Reformation. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of all that great affair will make appear, that thoſe who have Sworn the ruin of the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> fall upon God himſelf, which will not be for their advantage.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>This new Preacher carries it very high, but what did you an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to all this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>As he had more advantage over me, than I had over my Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:66400:83"/>I was obliged to ſuffer; the match being unequal. But I reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to let the diſcourſe continue, and to retain the principal things he ſhould oppoſe me with, to be infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of by you. Is any thing of theſe Facts falſe, that this man laid, thus as I have recited them?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>No: But though the Facts that he told you be true, it is not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that the Concluſions he draws from thence are very good; which we will examine at one time. But for the preſent I will not interrupt you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>Since you deſire it, I will continue to tell you what I can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member of a Converſation, which appeared to me in ſome places ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing above my Capacity. I hear, continued our Civil Lawyer, that this Gentleman has obliged himſelf to prove to you, that the courſe they take at preſent in <hi>France,</hi> againſt our poor Proteſtants, is quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Intereſts of the King and State. Give me leave, Sir, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent you ſeveral things upon that
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:66400:84"/>point. Firſt, is it not true, that it is againſt the Kings Intereſts to depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulate the Kingdom. There are ſtill in <hi>France,</hi> near two Millions of Souls of the Reformed Religion: If all theſe perſons were away, their abſence would certainly make a conſiderable Breach. There is no body but knows, that the force of States depends on the multitude of Inhabitants: It is this that makes the United Provinces ſo powerful. It is incredible that ſo little a State can reſiſt ſo powerful E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and carry it's name to the end of the World; which only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from the prodigious multitude of Inhabitants which are there. It is this that makes Arts flouriſh there, Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity being the Mother of Induſtry. It is the cauſe of the Commerce, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Territory being too little to nouriſh ſo many Men, they have been obliged to go ſeek to the very ends of the World, the neceſſaries that their own Country could not furniſh them with. And in ſeeking wherewith to keep them alive, and that they might not be famiſhed, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:66400:84"/>has made them find out immenſe Riches. The King knows very well, that the force of a Prince conſiſts in the multitude of Subjects. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he has made ſeveral Declarations in favour of thoſe to whom God grants great Families, and who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the more contribute to populate the Kingdom. He has ordered, that thoſe Victuallars who have have two Children, ſhould enjoy exemption from all Taxes, Impoſts, Subſidies, Collects, and quartering of Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. It is his will, that the Nobles who have the ſame number of living Children, have two thouſand Livers of yearly penſion out of the publick Revenues; and for the exciting young people to marry themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, he orders by another Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that the young married ſhall not be ſubject, till the age of five and twenty years, to any publick Charges. It is to this intent, that ſuch diverſe Declarations have been made by his Majeſty, which forbid all his Subjects to leave the Kingdom, and go inhabit elſe-where. By all
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:66400:85"/>theſe Courſes the King would get and keep Subjects. But his Majeſty by the Declarations which have been made againſt the Reformed, has loſt twenty times more Subjects than he can have gained, or kept by thoſe other ways, which his prudence, or that of his Miniſters had ſuggeſted to him. It will be made appear to him, if he pleaſes, that within theſe fifteen years, his Declarations againſt the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> have drove away of them out of <hi>France,</hi> above ſixty or four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore thouſand. All the Frontiere Provinces of <hi>England, Holland,</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> as <hi>Normandy, Campagne,</hi> and <hi>Picardy,</hi> are already ſenſible of this; particularly the City of <hi>Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens.</hi> Since the Temple has been ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the <hi>Hugonots</hi> of that City, it is certain, that the moſt part of their Merchants have retired them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into forreign Countries, and that they have carried with them, at leaſt twelve or fourteen hundred thouſand Livers of Riches out of the Kingdom, and which will never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn into it. In caſe they would but
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:66400:85"/>make the leaſt attention upon this point, it would appear, that it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, but that the Kingdom will be deſerted by this Courſe. It is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that all the Reformed who loſe their Goods and Eſtates, by what is called the diſgraces of Fortune, do quit the Kingdom; becauſe that their Religion hinders them from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering themſelves by any means. In chacing away all thoſe who bear the Arms of the Guards <hi>du Corps,</hi> of the Muſqueteers, and the Gendarmes, and all the Kings Houſehold; in taking the Commiſſions from ſeveral thouſands of Commiſſaries, who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved upon their Commſſions, in neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting the Officers, and refuſing them advancement: In a word, in taking away, as they do, the means of ſubſiſting from an infinite number of <hi>Hugonots,</hi> who cannot ſubſiſt of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; they are drove out of the Kingdom; and all forreign Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries are ſeen covered with <hi>French</hi>-men, who ſeek for employ, and the means of ſubſiſting, that are refuſed them in their own Country. I look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:66400:86"/>upon it as a certain thing, that of 50 thouſand, that the Rigour which is exerciſed againſt us, reduces into this eſtate, there are not five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred who turn Catholicks, all the others are as many loſt Subjects for the King. They are much deceived, if they believe that little is loſt in loſing people who have hardly any thing. For it is certain, that the Armies of a State are almoſt wholly compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of ſuch ſort of people; It is the induſtry of ſuch perſons who keep up Commerce and Arts. There is a City upon the Frontiers of <hi>Champagne,</hi> which formerly belonged to the Dukes of <hi>Bouillon,</hi> touching which I am informed, they make great brags to the King, that when he took poſſeſſion of it, that City was almoſt wholly Proteſtants, and that at preſent the number of the Catholicks much ſurpaſſes that of the others. But they tell not the King what was told me; that the ſeverity with which they treated the Reformed, has obliged them to retire; that the Catholicks which they fill the City with are Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:66400:86"/>and poor Wretches: That of a good City, they have made of it a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat for people who have nothing, and who are a charge to the Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty; that thoſe Catholicks the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is filled with, by expelling the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Inhabitants, come from the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs and neighbouring Villages. Thus the King gains no new Subjects, though the City gains new Inhabitants; and he loſes all the good Subjects, who go away and ſeek for repoſe elſewhere, and carry with them what Riches they have. The ſame thing happens in the Provinces, bordering upon <hi>Swizzerland</hi> and <hi>Geneva:</hi> They are not ſenſible yet of this diminution, but they will one day find it. Beſides, they may aſſure the King, that all thoſe zealous Convertours, who brag to him, that they increaſe the Catholick Church, will much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to deſart his Kingdom. It is certain, that of thoſe who change Religion to become Catholicks, there is not the fourth part, I dare ſay the ſixth, who perſevere in the Religion that they have embraced: They
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:66400:87"/>changed out of Intereſt, Lightneſs, Fear, Love, or ſome other paſſion which ſurprized them. When paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is cooled, reaſon returns, thoſe people are aſhamed of their change, and their Conſciences become awake. And as the moſt part have as little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit in <hi>France,</hi> as in another State, it little imports them where they are, and they go away to avoid the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of the Edicts againſt Relap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
                  <p>At that place our Doctor ſtopped a little, appeared penſive, and thus renewed. I am going to enter upon a nice Subject; I have no mind to offend any one, but I cannot forbear telling the truth. We are all good <hi>French-men;</hi> but the King has much more intereſt to preſerve his <hi>Hugonot</hi> Subjects than all the others, ſince it is the only Party of whoſe fidelity he can be ſecured. Give me leave, Sir, to handle this point more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. it is certain, that the great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes that <hi>France</hi> can have, are with <hi>Spain</hi> and with the Emperour: There is not a Family in <hi>Europe,</hi> that can
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:66400:87"/>give ombrage to that of <hi>France,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> Since <hi>Charles</hi> the 5th, that Houſe has ever aſpired to the Univerſal Monarchy. It is true that the King has brought it very low at preſent, and made it fall very much from its High preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. But in fine, it is the Courſe of the world, which is humbled to day to be raiſed again to morrow. The Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> has raiſed it ſelf from a very low Degree; it ſtill reigns in <hi>Spain, Germany,</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> that is to ſay, almoſt over the half of <hi>Europe;</hi> and when theſe large territories become ſenſible of their force, and to be animated by a great Chief; they may put <hi>Fance</hi> as hard to it as they did formerly. It is therefore certain, that the great Intereſt of our State, is to be always on the Guard on the ſide of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and deprive it of its Allyes, and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken its Subjects, and manage Allian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and form Adherences againſt it, and extirpate out of <hi>France</hi> all that might favour it, and entertain there all that is moſt oppoſite to it. And
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:66400:88"/>this already makes appear how much intereſt the King has not to ruine a Party, that can never enter into Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence with <hi>Spain.</hi> The Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> has conſerved ſo great a fury againſt the Proteſtants, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants conſerve ſo much reſentment for the violences that they have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered by the Princes of that Houſe, that thoſe two Parties are abſolutely irreconcilable. It is not the ſame thing with the other Parties of the State. It is true, that there is ſome natural antipathy between a <hi>French</hi>-man and a <hi>Spaniard;</hi> but you are too well acquainted with the Hiſtory of our age, Sir, to be ignorant, that notwithſtanding thoſe antipathies the Intereſts of the <hi>Grandees</hi> has of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten made ſuch great engagements with <hi>Spain,</hi> that they had like to have ruined the State. The Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the League, the entry of the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> into <hi>France,</hi> and the intentions that the wicked <hi>French</hi>-men then had, to receive a King foom the hands of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> are Warrants for what I advance. I
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:66400:88"/>could ſay ſomething more new, and add ſeveral ſtories of our Grandees, who diſſatisfied with the Court, put themſelves into the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Party, made Treaties with that Crown, and would have been of very ill conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to the Kindom, if the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Genius of the ſtate had not fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced off it's effects. But though all the reſt of <hi>France</hi> ſhould enter into ſuch a mind, the <hi>Hugonots</hi> Party alone would be a Barriere to the State, and would ſhed to the very laſt drop of its blood that it might not fall under the Dominion of <hi>Spain.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>The King, in the State he is, has little need of keeping meaſures with any one for the becoming formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable to the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> he who makes all <hi>Europe</hi> tremble, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries the terrour of his Armes even into <hi>Africa.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>That is true: But wiſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as the King is have longer proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects; they do not onely conſider themſelves and their preſent State, they conſider Poſterity and the future, and take their Sureties againſt all
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:66400:89"/>that may happen. Be it as it will, our Civil Lawyer proceeding farther upon the matter told me, Let me beg of you, Sir, that we may ſpeak freely. Is it not true, that the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> has engagements infinitely greater with <hi>Spain</hi> and the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> than with <hi>France? Spain</hi> renders ſubmiſſions to the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> that <hi>France</hi> does not render it; <hi>Spain</hi> does not talk of the Liberties of its Church, as they talk in <hi>France</hi> of the Liberties of the <hi>Gallicane</hi> Church, as theſe Liberties paſs at <hi>Rome</hi> for Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, or attempts againſt the Holy See. <hi>Spain</hi> is ſubmitted to the Tribunal of the Inquiſition, <hi>France</hi> rejects it, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in what it has of Good. In fine, <hi>Spain</hi> keeps Faith and does Homage to the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> for one part of its States, as the Kingdoms of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> and <hi>Arragon;</hi> and on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary the Kings of <hi>France</hi> will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on the Pope for Temporality, and hold only their State of God and their Swords. In one word, theſe engagements between <hi>Spain</hi> and the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> are ſuch, that this
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:66400:89"/>Court does not at all ballance, when it is to take the <hi>French</hi> or <hi>Spaniſh</hi> ſide; and never kept it ſelf neuter, but when it feared the Forces of <hi>France.</hi> Wherefore the <hi>Italian</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Party, are to be looked upon as the ſame Party. The King of <hi>Spain</hi> is Maſter of moſt part of <hi>Italy:</hi> The Popes are often <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> by Birth, and they are ever ſo by inclination; the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Faction amongſt the Cardinals is ever the moſt numerous. Thus the great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the King and of <hi>France,</hi> is to be ever upon the Guard againſt the <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> Faction, which can eaſily become <hi>Spaniſh.</hi> Now this <hi>Italian</hi> Party is not only in <hi>Spain</hi> and in <hi>Italy;</hi> it is in <hi>Germany,</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and every where elſe; it is the Body of the Clergy. One cannot be ignorant of the engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that all the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Clergy has neceſſarily with the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi> This Court is the Head, the Clergy is the Body, the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticks and Monks are the Members, and all theſe Members move by the Orders of the Head. Again, I have no
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:66400:90"/>Deſign to chocque the Gentlemen Clergy, whoſe perſons I reſpect; I do not doubt but that they have good <hi>French</hi> Hearts; But in fine, they have their Maximes of Conſcience; they are of a Religion, and they muſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low its Principles. Now the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of their Religion binds them to the Holy See, and its preſervation preferably to all things; moreover, Intereſt makes illuſion in Hearts and Minds. Their Intereſt obliges them to take the Popes part, who is their Preſerver and Protectour; and what they do out of intereſt, they perſuade themſelves that they do it out of Conſcience. Firſt, it may be ſaid of the Monks, that all the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes they have in <hi>France,</hi> are as many Citadels that the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> has in the Kingdom. Thoſe great Societies have withdrawn themſelves from the Dominion of the Biſhops, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend immediately on the Holy See; they have all their Generals of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders at <hi>Rome;</hi> and thoſe Generals who are <hi>Italians</hi> and <hi>Spaniards,</hi> are the Soul of the Society; they are
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:66400:90"/>obliged to follow their Opinions and their Orders; the <hi>Italian</hi> Divinity is the Divinity of the Cloiſters. Thus the King may reckon, that all the Monks look upon him as the Pope's Subject, as being lyable to be Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated, his Kingdom put under an Eccleſiaſtical Cenſure, his Subjects diſpenſed and releaſed from the Oath of Fidelity, and his States given by the Pope to another Prince. And every time that this happens, they will believe themſelves obliged, out of Conſcience, to obey the Pope. If in thoſe Orders of Monks there hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens to be ſome particular One, who follow other Principles, it is certain that they are in no Number, and do not hinder that the Body of the Monks is abſolutely in the Intereſts of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and by conſequence in that of <hi>Spain.</hi> Thus you ſee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready a conſiderable Party of whoſe Fidelity the Kings of <hi>France</hi> cannot be aſſured. And what is this Party One may ſay that it is all <hi>France:</hi> for the begging Monks and the Jeſuits are Maſters of all the Conſciences; they
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:66400:91"/>are Confeſſors, they are Directors, they perſuade what they will to thoſe that are devoted to them. The Houſe of <hi>Bourbon</hi> ought not to doubt of this truth, if it never ſo little calls to mind the endeavours that were uſed by the Monks for the forcing from it the Crown, when the Race of the <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lois</hi> came to fail. It is againſt this ſo conſiderable Party that the State ought to take its Precautions, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving that other Party which can never be of intelligence with this; it is that of the Reformed. Hiſtory tells us how impoſſible it is to be long without having Diſputes with the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi> It is always attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and one is obliged to defend ones ſelf againſt its enterpriſes. It is capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of ſetting great Engines a going, of making Engagements and Allian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: It had twenty times like to have ruined <hi>Germany,</hi> it has dethroned great Emperours, it has likewiſe cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed great troubles in <hi>France,</hi> and one cannot be too ſecure againſt its ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="179" facs="tcp:66400:91"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>I fancy that your <hi>Hugonot</hi>'s Advocate would not ſpare the reſt of the Clergy, and that he endeavoured to prove that we can be no more aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of their Fidelity than of that of the Religious.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>What you have already heard may make you eaſily divine that, for the giving the more force to what he had to ſay againſt our Divines, he prevented what might have been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected. If you underſtood theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Sir, ſaid he to me, you could tell me that our Clergy of <hi>France</hi> teach a Divinity wholly different from that of <hi>Rome;</hi> that all make profeſſion of holding for the Liberties of the <hi>Gallicane</hi> Church; the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Articles of which are,
<list>
                        <item>1. That the King of <hi>France</hi> cannot be Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated by the Pope.</item>
                        <item>2. That an Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Cenſure cannot be laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Kingdome.</item>
                        <item>3. That it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be given to others.</item>
                        <item>4. That the Pope has nothing to do with the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porality of Kings.</item>
                        <item>5. That he is not Infallible.</item>
                        <item>6. That he is inferiour to the Council.</item>
                     </list> Theſe, you would tell
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:66400:92"/>me, are the Maximes of the <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> that have often cenſured the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Propoſitions. This Divinity is maintained by the Authority of the Parliaments, who have often declared the Bulls of the Pope abuſive, null, ſcandalous and impious, and have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed from the Execution of theſe Bulls, when they found them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Liberties of the <hi>Gallicane</hi> Church. The Court of Parliament aſſembled at <hi>Tours,</hi> during the League, cauſed the Bulls of Excommunication to be burnt by the hands of the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner, that had been publiſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Henry</hi> the Third and <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth. This is all ſine and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent, if you pleaſe, but theſe fair appearances have no ſtock; I do not ſpeak of the Divinity of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which is that of the Politici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; I ſpeak of the Divinity of the Clergy.</p>
                  <p>Once more, added he, I do not at all doubt of the Fidelity of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of <hi>France</hi> to their King; but they ſhall never perſwade me, that this Fidelity and Zeal for their Prince
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:66400:92"/>is without exception; and I make no other exception againſt it than what they themſelves make: Will you hear they themſelves ſpeak? Read the Harangue that Cardinal <hi>du Perron</hi> made to the third Eſtate, in the name of all the Clergy of <hi>France,</hi> in the States, 1616, and remember that it is not the Cardinal <hi>du Perron</hi> who ſpeaks, it is the Clergy of <hi>France</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in a Body who ſpeak by the mouth of that Cardinal. All <hi>France</hi> ſeiſed with an horrour of the two hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Parricides that had been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the perſons of the two late Kings, both of them aſſaſſinated out of a falſe Zeal of Religion, would draw up a Formulary of Oath, and eſtabliſh a Fundamental Law of the State, which all the Subjects were to ſwear to; and this Law bore, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one ſhould make Oath of ac-acknowledging and believing, that our Kings for their Temporalities do not depend on any one ſoever but on God; that it is not lawful for any cauſe ſoever to aſſaſſinate Kings; that even for cauſes of Hereſie &amp; of Schiſm
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:66400:93"/>Kings cannot be Depoſed, nor their Subjects Abſolved from their Oath of Fidelity, nor upon any other pretext ſoever. This Law, methinks, is the ſecurity of Kings, this is a Doctrine which all the <hi>Hugonots</hi> are ready to ſign with their Blood. What did the Clergy of <hi>France</hi> do thereupon? It formally oppoſed that Law; (divers Works of Cardinal <hi>du Perron, p.</hi> 600 and following) they were willing to acknowledge the Independancy of Kings, in regard of the Temporalty; they conſented that Anathema ſhould be pronounced againſt the aſſaſſinates of Kings. But they would never paſs the laſt Article; that for what cauſe ſoever it was, a King cannot be Depoſed by the Pope, ſtript of his States, and his Subjects abſolved from the Oath of Fidelity. He who ſpoke for them, alledged all the examples of Emperours and of Kings, who had been Depoſed and Excommunicated by Popes, upon account of refuſing Obedience to the Holy See, &amp; appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them; he alledged the example of St. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the Second, who Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:66400:93"/>
                     <hi>Philip</hi> the Firſt, and laid an Eccleſiaſtical Cenſure upon his Kingdom, becauſe he had repudiated his Wife <hi>Bertha,</hi> Daughter of a Count of <hi>Holland,</hi> to Marry <hi>Bertrade</hi> Wife of <hi>Foulques</hi> Count <hi>d' Anjou,</hi> then ſtill alive. He made uſe of the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of <hi>Paul Emile,</hi> who ſaid, that Pope <hi>Zacharias</hi> diſpenſed the <hi>French</hi> from the Oath of Fidelity that they had made to <hi>Chilperick.</hi> Theſe two Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were not Hereticks; yet the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of <hi>France</hi> approved their having been ſtript of their States by the Popes; which makes appear, that the Clergy in the bottom judges that the Pope has Right to lay an Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Conſure upon the Kingdom of <hi>France,</hi> and to depoſe its Kings for any other cauſe as well as that or Hereſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e. Is it not to abuſe the World, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs on one ſide that the Temporalty of Kings does not depend on the Pope, and eſtabliſh on the other, that the Pope may in certain occaſions Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict theſe Kings, Excommunicate them, and Abſolve their Subjects from the Oath of Fidelity? In ſine, this is
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:66400:94"/>the reſult of that famous Opinion of the Clergy of <hi>France.</hi> So that if Chriſtians are conſtrained to defend their Religion and their lives againſt Heretick Princes or Apoſtates, from their Fidelity to whom they have been Abſolved, the Politick Chriſtian Laws does not permit them any thing more than what is permitted by Military Laws, and by the Right of Nations, to wit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> open War, and not Aſſaſſina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Clandeſtine Conſpiracies: that is to ſay, that when a Pope has decl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ed a Prince deprived of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tates, his Subjects may ſet up the Standard of Rebellion, declare War againſt him, refuſe him Obedience, and kill him if they can meet him, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it be with arms in their hand, and by the ordinary courſe of War. I cannot comprehend how one can be ſecured of the Fidelity of thoſe who hold ſuch like Maximes. For in fine, Kings are not inſallible, and if they happen to do any thing that the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> judges worthy of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication and Interdiction, they are Kings without Kingdoms and
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:66400:94"/>Subjects, according to our Clergy of <hi>France,</hi> as well as according to the Divines of <hi>Italy.</hi> But perhaps that the <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> which is the Depoſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the <hi>French</hi> Divinity, does not receive theſe Maximes ſo fatal to the ſafety of Kings: Let us ſee what it has done. In the Month of <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> 1587, becauſe that <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, for the ſecurity of his Perſon and of his State, made a Treaty with the Reſiſters, or the <hi>German</hi> Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, the <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> without ſtaying for the Deciſions of <hi>Rome,</hi> made a ſecret Reſult, which ſaid, That the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment might be taken from Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, who were not found ſuch as they ought to be, as the adminiſtration from a ſuſpected Tutour: This was known by the King, he ſent for the <hi>Sorbonne</hi> ſome days after, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of it. After the death of the Princes of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> which happen'd at <hi>Blois,</hi> the <hi>Sorbonne</hi> did much worſe: they declared and cauſed to be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in all parts of <hi>Paris,</hi> That all the People of that Kingdom were Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved from the Oaths of Fidelity that
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:66400:95"/>they had ſworn to <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Valois,</hi> heretofore their King: they razed his name out of the publick Prayers, and made known to the People that they might with ſafe Conſcience unite, arm and contribute to make War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, as a Tyrant. If I would add to that the Story that I know this Gentleman told you concerning the Death of the late King of <hi>England,</hi> we ſhould find that the <hi>Sorbonne</hi> has ever been of the ſame Opinion. Let things be told as they are, every time that our Kings ſhall have aſſairs that will carry them to extremity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Clergy of <hi>France</hi> will ſuppreſs the diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents while that affairs go well for the Court of <hi>France;</hi> but if things turn otherways, the dictates of our Divines againſt the King will not fail to break out. Every ſincere perſon will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that it has never been otherwiſe than ſo, and that it will be always thus; which may be obſerved in the very leaſt diſputes. By example, in that the King has now lately had with the Pope upon the account of the
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:66400:95"/>Regality and of the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbaniſts,</hi> the publick has ſeen a Letter from the Clergy Addreſſed to the King when he departed to viſit the Frontiers of the Low-Countries; In that Letter theſe Gentlemen promiſe the King, let whatever be the iſſue of his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes with the Pope, they will be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways inviolably fixed to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Intereſts. But we know from good hands, that the Archbiſhop of <hi>Paris</hi> and the Sieur <hi>Roſe</hi> Secretary of the Cabinet, are the ſole Authors of that Letter; the Biſhops have almoſt openly diſavowed it. And this makes it apparent enough, that in this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute they were of the Popes ſide. Muſt it not then be confeſſed, that it is the King's Intereſt to preſerve the only Party that makes Oath of Fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to him without exception and without reſerve, that can never have engagements contrary to his Service, either with <hi>Spain</hi> or the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> or with the revolted Clergy favouring the Enemies of the State? And it is well known, that in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, while that all
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:66400:96"/>the Corporations of the Kingdom were in an actual Rebellion againſt their Prince, the <hi>Hugonot</hi> was the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one which remained Loyal. If it was neceſſary to add any thing more, purſued our Civil Lawyer, for to prove that it is the King's Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to protect the Reformed in his States, one might ſay that the Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances that have been made with Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Proteſtants have not been diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantageous to the State. Since the year, 1630, its engagements with <hi>England, Holland, Sweden,</hi> and the Elector of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> have been a great help towards its humbling the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> Cardinal <hi>Richlieu</hi> ſucceſsfully employed the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> for to puniſh the pride to which that Houſe was mounted after the defeat of the <hi>Palatine</hi> Houſe that had accepted the Crown of <hi>Bohemia.</hi> And it is well enough known, that the Protection that the King gave the Proteſtants in his Territories, facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated thoſe Foreign Engagements and Alliances. Thus our Orator ended and made a pauſe at this place.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="189" facs="tcp:66400:96"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>He has forgot a great Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, That which is againſt the Peace of a State is ever againſt his Intereſts who governs it: Nothing is more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compatible with Peace, than diverſity of Religions.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>He did not forget it, but he thought he had ſaid enough for one time, and referred what he had more to ſay till the next day. This morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſour Gentleman returned, and as what was ſaid is freſher in my memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, perhaps I ſhall give you a more exact account. I know very well, continued our <hi>Hugonot</hi> Civil Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer, that I am to Diſpute to day a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a pompous Maximed that has all appearances for it, that covers it ſelf with the habit of Devotion, and againſt which the Bigots ſay one can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not declare without impiety. But provided we be heard, and that we are permitted to diſtinguiſh and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain our ſelves, we ſhall appear no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs than impious. If it be ſaid that nothing is more deſirable by a good Prince, than to ſee all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects live in the true Religion; we
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:66400:97"/>grant it; if it be added, that for the reuniting minds, and bringing them all to think the ſame thing in matters that may be controverted, he ought to employ all the means that Chriſtian Morality ſuggeſts and approves; we will likewiſe avow it. But all this can neither make us affraid, nor do us any hurt. Moral Chriſtianity does not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer that ill be done, that good may come on it: It will never Counſel the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union of Religion, by violence and breaking of Words. If it be added, that this Maxim is as true in Policy, as it is in Morality; and that it is the intereſt of a State, for its Conſervation, to have but one Religion, in ſuch a manner, that it cannot be great, flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing and peaceable, while that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of Religions are ſuffered and tolerated, we ſhall ſay that nothing can be advanced more falſe. Firſt of all, thoſe Gentlemen who maintain that Maxime with ſo much confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, do not think of what they do; they do not perceive that they make an Apology for all perſecuting Princes. If it be ſo, the Pagan Emperours had
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:66400:97"/>reaſon to arm againſt the Chriſtians, and to ſet whole Rivers of their blood a flowing. The Chriſtians ſeparated themſelves from their Society; they looked upon others as Enemies of God, and as the Devils Subjects; and good Policy, according to the Maxime that is taught our Kings, cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit that ſuch people ſhould be ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to live. If theſe Gentlemen might be believed, the Grand Seignior is but very ill Counſelled, to tollerate in his Territories the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; he could not be blamed if he let looſe his <hi>Janizaries</hi> upon the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and cauſed all their throats to be cut.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>That's a pretty fancy, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare a Chriſtian Prince, who is of the true Religion, to a <hi>Pagan</hi> Prince or Infidel. It is a Crime to perſecute the true Religion; but it is a work of great merit to extirpate Hereſie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prov.</speaker>
                  <p>Stay, and you ſhall know what he told me thereupon. There is not a man, ſaid he, but who's per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded that he's of the true Religion. The Grand Seignior believes himſelf
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:66400:98"/>in the way of Salvation, as the moſt Chriſtian King perſuades himſelf he is. Thus according to the principles of Morality, his Conſcience orders him do all that is poſſible for him to ſave his people, by forcing them to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of a Religion, which he believes to be the only way to Salvation. But you muſt eſpecially take notice, that we examine this Maxime according to the Rules of Policy. Now, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to theſe Rules, the Grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior is as well obliged to endeavour the Peace and Preſervation of his Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories, as the Chriſtian Princes are to endeavour the Preſervation of theirs. To refute this Maxime, I will only mention that ſo common ſaying, <hi>Divide &amp; Impera;</hi> Nouriſh Diviſion, and you will eaſily remain Maſter. When there are ſeveral Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in a State, provided that the Prince eſpouſes none of them; that Diviſion obliges each of the Parties to hold faſt to the Princes intereſts, for the having his Favour and Protection. If one of the Parties gets much ground of the other; and that the Prince
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:66400:98"/>likewiſe happens into this ſtrongeſt Party, provided that he hinders the weakeſt from being oppreſſed by the ſtrongeſt, it is clear that he cannot fail to be beloved and conſidered by all his Subjects. He would be belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the ſtrongeſt party, becauſe he himſelf was of it; the fear of loſing him would make them manage him. The weakeſt party would have love and acknowledgement for a Prince, whom it was indebted to for its Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity by the Protection it received. Add to all this, that ſuch people as are of contrary Religions cannot enter into the ſame Rebellion. Thus the Prince is always ſure to have a faithful Party. It is ever difficult that, in a State divided thus, great Conſpiracies can be contrived; for the one party continually watches the paces of the other. [<hi>Plutarchs</hi> Treatiſe of <hi>Iſis</hi> and <hi>Oſiris.</hi>] The Ancients have obſerved to us, that in <hi>Egypt</hi> there was almoſt as many Religions; as Cities, becauſe that they had diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Animals for Gods. At <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phis</hi> they adored the Oxe <hi>Apis,</hi> at <hi>Leon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>topolis</hi>
                     <pb n="194" facs="tcp:66400:99"/>the Lyon, at another place a Wolfe, in another City a Sheep, at another a Goat. And they were of ſo contrary Religions, that ſome eat the Annimals that their Neighbours adored, with deſign to vex them, and turn their Religion into Ridicule. [<hi>Diodorus,</hi> his 1. Book of his <hi>Biblio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiques.</hi>] The Kings of <hi>Egypt</hi> nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed this Diviſion, and found that it was the ſecurity of the State, becauſe that it hindred Conſpiracies. I leave it to Politicians to puſh the Specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions farther that may be made upon it, and content my ſelf with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, by which I make appear that it is very falſe, that a State can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be both peaceable and happy, when it tolerates ſeveral Religions. It would be requiſite to make the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the World, to ſay all that can be ſaid upon it: We ſhould ſpeak of thoſe great Empires, which inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſo many ſeveral Nations, and full as many Religions. It is certain, that one <hi>Paganiſme</hi> was more different from the other, than the Sects of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are different from one another;
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:66400:99"/>yet the <hi>Romans</hi> did not fail to render their Empire glorious and flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and it was never the Diverſity of Religions that troubled it's Peace. It has been obſerved, that they carried away the Gods and Spoils of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions whom they rendered Tributary, and that they adopted thoſe ſtrange Gods, and built them Temples in <hi>Rome.</hi> So that they nouriſhed this Diverſity of Religions, even in the very boſome and Capital of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, without the Peace being any way altered. If from the Conduct of the <hi>Pagans</hi> we pals to that of the Chriſtian Emperours, we ſhall ſee therein the ſame thing: That is they have tolerated the Diverſity of Sects amongſt the Chriſtians, without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicing the good of the State. The <hi>Novatians</hi> had their Churches, their Biſhops and their Prieſts, even in <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> that was the Capital of the Empire. They were not only tolerated there, but were likewiſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed. <hi>Conſtantine</hi> did the honour to their Biſhop <hi>Aceſius,</hi> to call him to the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> and to ask his
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:66400:100"/>Opinion upon the Decree that had been made, touching what day <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> ought to be celebrated upon. And when he the Great <hi>Theodoſius</hi> took the Reſolution to try to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile all the Sects by amicable confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, he Communicated his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to <hi>Nectarius,</hi> Biſhop of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks in <hi>Conſtantinople: Nectarius,</hi> who had not been brought up in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Affairs, conſulted able per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and amongſt others, he did the honour to <hi>Agelius,</hi> who was then Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of the <hi>Novatians,</hi> to ask him his advice. <hi>Agelius</hi> had a Deacon called <hi>Siſinnius,</hi> able and knowing, to whom he gave Commiſſion to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with <hi>Nectarius;</hi> and this <hi>Siſinni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> gave thereupon ſuch Counſel, as was approved by <hi>Nectarius</hi> and the Emperour. But as concerning <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius,</hi> they object againſt us the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of that Great Prince, in regard of the <hi>Arrians;</hi> they have compoſed his Hiſtory, they have put it into the hands of the Children of our Kings; they give them for a Model of their Conduct with us, that of <hi>Theodoſius</hi>
                     <pb n="197" facs="tcp:66400:100"/>with the Hereticks of his time. In truth they do us a great deal of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, to compare us with the <hi>Arrians,</hi> who were ſworn Enemies of Jeſus Chriſt, and by Conſequence of the Chriſtian Religion; and who had perſecuted the Church, even to effuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of blood: Yet we receive the ſix firſt General Councils, and deteſt all the Hereſies that the Church has con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned. I leave equitable people to judge if ſuch ſentiments as theſe are fit to he inſpired into young Princes. I add, that <hi>Theodoſius</hi> had promiſed nothing to the <hi>Arrians,</hi> he had not made any Treaty with them, nor had he given them any Edicts. And in fine, I ſay, that though <hi>Theodoſius</hi> made ſome ſevere Declarations againſt the <hi>Arrians;</hi> the moſt part of them were not executed. <hi>Socrates,</hi> his <hi>Eccl.</hi> Hiſt. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 2. The Conduct of <hi>Gratian</hi> a moſt Chriſtian Emperour, who gave liberty of Conſcience and exerciſe to all the Sects, except the <hi>Eunomians, Manicheans</hi> and <hi>Phoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> merits to be conſidered, for it is the Model wiſe Princes ought to regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:66400:101"/>themſelves by. That is to ſay, that when they are obliged to tolerate Divers Sects, their toleration ought not to reach to thoſe who ruin the very foundations of Chriſtianity, as the <hi>Eunomians,</hi> or <hi>Arrians,</hi> the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicheans,</hi> and the <hi>Photinians</hi> did, who were what the <hi>Socinians</hi> are at preſent, I could purſue the Hiſtory of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and make appear how in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing ages, the Religion was ſhared into ſeveral Branches, by the Schiſmes of <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> of <hi>Eutychus,</hi> and of the <hi>Monothelites,</hi> which filled the Eaſt; and yet the Empire kept ſtill ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. It was not thoſe Schiſmes in Religion, that gave Birth to that ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Empire of the <hi>Sarazins</hi> that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the <hi>Turks</hi> from the North, and cauſed thoſe Inundations of the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Nations, by which the Empire has been ruined. They will tell me that thoſe Schiſmes in Religion have often cauſed very great diſſorders in the State, I avow it. But from whence did that proceed? Becauſe that one party would have oppreſſed the other, and for that the Emperours and the
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:66400:101"/>Grandees of the Empire maintained thoſe ſeveral Parties, and armed them the one againſt the other. Thus the Toleration of ſeveral Religions was far from cauſing any diſorder, the troubles were only occaſioned by their not ſuffering Diverſity of Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. If the <hi>Eutycheans</hi> would have tolerated thoſe that were Orthodox, and that the Orthodox would have to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerated the <hi>Eutycheans,</hi> the Peace of the State had not been in the leaſt altered. It becomes thoſe Gentlemen to object the State <hi>France</hi> was in in the laſt age, for to prove that the toleration of ſeveral Religions in a State is very dangerous. From whence proceeded our Wars of Religion in <hi>France?</hi> Did they not ariſe from the violence that the Catholick Party would have uſed upon the Proteſtant Party? If they would have ſuffered one another, and if the Princes who governed the State had not conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ruin the Proteſtants by Sword, and by Fire, all the State would have been in a perfect Tranquillity. All this that I have ſaid does not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:66400:102"/>me from avowing, that there are occaſions in which a Prince may employ the Rigour of the Edicts, for to hinder the diverſity of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions; which is at the firſt Birth of Schiſms. But when a Schiſm is once formed, when a Sect is become nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous and ſtrong, it is to go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Spirit of the Goſpel to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy either violence or deceit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy this evil: eſpecially when a Prince who mounts upon the Throne, finds that diverſity of Religions e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed and tolerated: I maintain that for the Peace of the State he is obliged to continue that toleration which thoſe Sects are in poſſeſſion of. The United Provinces of the Low Countries can learn us, what ill the diverſity of Religions produces in a State when it is tolerated. They are daily reproached for including in their boſom all the Religions of <hi>Europe.</hi> I do not examine at preſent if that ſo general toleration for all ſorts of Sects is according to the principles of Religion; I am not very much of that Opinion. But I boldly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:66400:102"/>that, according to the Rules of Policy, this general toleration is what makes the ſtrength and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of that Republick: it is that which invites thither ſo great a number of people; and it is what keeps up Trade there. All thoſe Sects have different Intereſts in regard of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; but all conſpire to the good and preſervation of a State in which they enjoy a repoſe that they would not find elſewhere. In fine, ſince it is the Religion of <hi>France</hi> that is in diſpute, let us draw our Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples from <hi>France</hi> it ſelf. Had not the State like to have periſhed in the laſt age by the fury of thoſe who were reſolved to ſuffer but one Religion in <hi>France?</hi> Never was this State ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, as ſince the Peace was re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by the Edicts of Pacification. Shew me an age in our Hiſtory, in which <hi>France</hi> was ſo glorious and ſo Triumphing as within theſe fourſcore years; that is to ſay, ſince that the two Religions were obliged to ſuffer one another by the diſpoſition of the Edicts? After that <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:66400:103"/>had pacified the affairs of Religion, it may be ſaid that he had all manner of advantage over his Enemies. When Cardinal <hi>de Richlieu</hi> had finiſhed what he deſigned againſt the Proteſtants, in depriving them of their Cities of Surety, and that he had reſtored Peace to them, he raiſed the glory of the Monarchy by the Alliance with the <hi>Swedes</hi> higher than it had ever been. The diverſity of Religions that is ſtill in <hi>France</hi> does not hinder our glorious Monarchy from being the admiration of all the Univerſe, and the terrour of all <hi>Europe.</hi> In a word, the State will never come to any trouble by the diverſity of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, as long as the Proteſtants are protected and tolerated. As long as the King pleaſes he will have in them Subjects of an inviolable Fidelity; and for the leaſt kindneſs he has for them, he might draw from their veins to the very laſt drop of their blood for his Service. It was thus that our Converſations ended. For my part I was not verſed enough in Ancient and Modern Hiſtory to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:66400:103"/>all this. You would oblige me, Sir, to tell me your thoughts upon it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Par.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe Gentlemen took time to think of their Difficulties before they propoſed them to you, it is juſt that we do the like to think of our Anſwers. It is enough for this day that we have heard them.</p>
               </sp>
               <trailer>The End of the Dialogues.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="204" facs="tcp:66400:104"/>
               <p>SInce that theſe Dialogues were fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, there fell into the Authors hands a Letter from the Sieur <hi>Peliſſon</hi> a famous Convert, and a more famous Convertour: It was believed to be worthy of the Publick curioſity, and that nothing was more proper to make appear how Apoſtolical the manner is that is made uſe of for the Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Souls. Nothing more reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles the Conduct of the Apoſtles, who went from place to place ſpreading the Riches of Grace to the contempt of thoſe of Nature, than the Charity of theſe Gentlemen, who ſpread eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where the Riches of Nature, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite men to Grace. <hi>Verſailles</hi> the 12. of <hi>June,</hi> 1677.</p>
               <p>Sir, To anſwer the Letter you did me the honour to write me on <hi>May</hi> the 21th. beſides what <hi>M. de le Tour Dalier</hi> ſends you, I ſend you a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py of a Memorial, that I have ſent to ſome of my Lords, the Biſhops of <hi>Languedock,</hi> upon ſuch Informations as they required of me. You will therein ſee, Sir, that I have propos'd
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:66400:104"/>you as an example to all the others, being but what you merit; and in the ſecond place, without limiting any ſum, you may with the ſame Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy, and in the Conditions of this Memorial, proceed as far as you pleaſe, as well at <hi>Pragelas,</hi> as in all the reſt of your Dioceſs, in point of little Gratifications to the New Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts.</p>
               <p>M. <hi>Dalier</hi> has took upon him to ſend you a Letter of Credit for the taking up thoſe little ſums which may become great ones, according as you ſhall have occaſion; and for my part I heartily wiſh, Sir, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge ſeveral of your Bills of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, not only for three or for ſix thouſand Livers, but for ten and for fifteen, and for as much as you pleaſe. I ſhall not be ſo happy as to have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to complain of their being too much. If you ask me, Sir, how this agrees with the ſmallneſs of our Stocks, and the deſign of endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame through all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; I ſhall place at the beginning of my Story that which made the
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:66400:105"/>Widows Oyland Flower increaſe, and which multip lied the five Loaves. Beſides, all Converſions are not made in a day: that while the time runs, the ſtock advances: that theſe good ſucceſſes have made the King determine to diſpoſe of St. <hi>Germains</hi> and <hi>Cluny</hi> only to theſe ſort of good works; that Credit will be found to make ordinary advances at need up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe Abbeys: that if we ſaw ſo great ſucceſs and ſo much of ſtock en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in the future, we might ſtop. or demand other helps from the King which his Piety would hardly refuſe the furniſhing, without reckoning thoſe of which ſome overtures have been made to him that he has not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected.</p>
               <p>As for M. <hi>de Gilliers,</hi> I do not ſee in your Letter, Sir, if he is to be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, or is already a Convert; in the firſt caſe I can charge my ſelf with propoſing to the King what you ſhall judge moſt convenient, in making it known to me more preciſely. In the ſecond caſe, that is to ſay, if he or his Family have been Converted for ſome
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:66400:105"/>time, you muſt get ſome other to ſpeak to the King than I who have ſolemnly renounced, and as by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, not to propoſe to him on my part any other expence than that of making Converſions.</p>
               <p>I admire, Sir, the work that God has wrought by your hands, and by M. <hi>Dalier,</hi> for your General Hoſpital. I fancy it to be as much as the taking of <hi>Valenciennes, Cambray,</hi> and St. <hi>Omers.</hi> I ſhall have the honour to write more particularly to you at the little Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly that <hi>Whitſon</hi> holy-days has diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, inſomuch that I have not yet ſeen the Chief Preſident, who returns but to morrow from <hi>Baſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ville.</hi> Be pleaſed, Sir, to continue to honour me with ſome part of your favour: and if you will do me a great deal of good, and a very great kindneſs, with ſome part likewiſe in your moſt ſecret Prayers, be it in the Cell, or be it at the Altar. I am with all poſſible reſpect.</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute> 
                  <signed>Your moſt humble, and moſt obedient Servant <hi>Peliſſon Fontanier.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <pb n="208" facs="tcp:66400:106"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A</hi> POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <p>THere has ben a great number of Converſions made in the Valleys of <hi>Pragelas,</hi> by the Cares of M. <hi>de Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble,</hi> and the Company of the Propagati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Faith in the ſame City, and by ſome Miſſionaries of the Company of Jeſus: Inſomuch that without other di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution than about two thouſand Crowns in all, ſent at ſeveral times, there are are well certified Liſts of ſeven or eight hundred perſons returned to the Church. Some of my Lords the Biſhops having done me the honour to write me word, that they likewiſe ſaw ſeveral Converſions that might be made in their Dioceſſes, if moneys were ſent them. I made anſwer by order from the King, that it was not poſſible to ſend Moneys into ſo many places; but that every one ſhould labour on his ſide, and give notice of the Converſions that were to be made in the conſiderable Families, that the King might think of it and provide accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly: Neither ſhould any occaſion be let ſlip for the converting the Families of the
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:66400:106"/>people, when it coſts but little, as had been ſeen in thoſe Vallies, that for two, three, four or five Piſtols, very nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Families had been gained. I even told them they might mount to an hundred <hi>Francs,</hi> without my needing to have any New Order from his Majeſty to acquit the Bills of Exchange that ſhould be drawn upon me. This was very reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly performed in regard of thoſe to whom I had written.</p>
               <p>I ſaid the ſame thing to M. <hi>Potel</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary of the Commands of the Duke of <hi>Vernuil,</hi> at his going to the States of <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guedock,</hi> that he might make it known to my Lords the Biſhops who ſhould be aſſembled there; and I have ſince con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed him by Letters, and ſo much the more willingly, being the King, excited by the good ſucceſs, had lately made a new Fond, which is the third of all the Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomats expedited or to be expedited ſince the Month of <hi>December</hi> laſt, which he only deſigns for this uſe, which will not begin to produce before the beginning of the next year: but from which may be hoped a perpetual ſuccour for the future. Things are in the ſame ſtate, and though
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:66400:107"/>that this Fond is not yet come, means will be found to pay the Bills that ſhall be drawn upon me for that effect. But the following conditions muſt be obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1.</hi> That they be not unknown perſons, or little known, and without Character, who draw thoſe Bills of Exchange upon me.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2.</hi> That every one be accompanied with an abjuration certified by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of the Dioceſs. M. <hi>l'Intendant,</hi> or any other perſon in a conſiderable Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy, and with an Acquittance from a publick hand for the diſcharge of the Sieur <hi>Soutain,</hi> Commiſſary for his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty for the receiving the Temporalties of the Abbeys of <hi>Cluny</hi> and St. <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main des Prez,</hi> together with the thirds of the Oeconomats deſign for New Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3.</hi> That theſe abjurations be ſince the Month of <hi>November laſt, 1676.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>4.</hi> That though they might mount to an hundred <hi>Francs</hi> that is not to ſay that it is intended they always ſhould do ſo, it being neceſſary to be as wary therein as can be; firſt for the ſpreading
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:66400:107"/>this dew upon the more people; and then again, becauſe that if an hundred <hi>Francs</hi> be given to leſſer perſons without any Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily that follows them, thoſe who are raiſed the leaſt higher or train after them a number of Children, will demand much greater ſums.</item>
               </list>
               <p>My Lords the Prelates, or others, who ſhall charitably take upon them theſe kind of Cares, cannot better make their Court to the King, before whoſe eyes all theſe Liſts of the Converts paſs, than in imitating what has been done in the Dioceſs of <hi>Grenoble,</hi> where they hardly ever mounted to that ſum of an hundred Francs, and were almoſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways much below it.</p>
               <p>Which does not however hinder, that for more conſiderable performances, I having firſt notice, greater ſums ſhall be furniſhed, according as his Majeſty, to whom it ſhall be made known, ſhall iudge convenient.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:66400:108" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 11. l. 8. for <hi>evoqued,</hi> r. <hi>removed.</hi> p. 19. l. 15. for <hi>had given,</hi> r. <hi>had not given.</hi> p. 22. l. 2. for <hi>regard to,</hi> r. <hi>regard had to.</hi> p. 25. l. 26. for <hi>Fiefarons, Fee-farms,</hi> p. 31. l. 22. for <hi>ſcale,</hi> r. <hi>ſeal.</hi> p. 33. l. 12. for <hi>to our,</hi> r. <hi>our.</hi> l. 15. for <hi>our,</hi> r. <hi>to our.</hi> p. 34. l. 25. for <hi>modeſt,</hi> r. <hi>modeſt by force.</hi> l. 26. for <hi>indignation,</hi> r. <hi>inclination.</hi> p. 43. l. 22. for <hi>Baptiſm of Faith,</hi> r. <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm of Laicks.</hi> p. 69. l. 14. for <hi>Lives,</hi> r. <hi>Books.</hi> p. 78. l. 14. for <hi>Bedunt,</hi> r. <hi>Pedant.</hi> p. 107. l. 1. for <hi>Schupe,</hi> r. <hi>Schuyt.</hi> p. 146. l. 14 for <hi>nutas,</hi> r. <hi>nutat.</hi> p. 150. l. 7. for <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> r. <hi>Profuſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:66400:108"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
